<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Microsoft Security Blog</title>
	<atom:link href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/</link>
	<description>Expert coverage of cybersecurity topics</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 01:23:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.7.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Disrupting active exploitation of on-premises SharePoint vulnerabilities</title>
		<link>https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/2025/07/22/disrupting-active-exploitation-of-on-premises-sharepoint-vulnerabilities/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Microsoft Threat Intelligence]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/?p=141368</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Microsoft has observed two named Chinese nation-state actors, Linen Typhoon and Violet Typhoon, exploiting vulnerabilities targeting internet-facing SharePoint servers. In addition, we have observed another China-based threat actor, tracked as Storm-2603, exploiting these vulnerabilities. Microsoft has released new comprehensive security updates for all supported versions of SharePoint Server (Subscription Edition, 2019, and 2016) that protect customers against these new vulnerabilities. Customers should apply these updates immediately to ensure they are protected.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/2025/07/22/disrupting-active-exploitation-of-on-premises-sharepoint-vulnerabilities/">Disrupting active exploitation of on-premises SharePoint vulnerabilities</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog">Microsoft Security Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><strong>July 23, 2025 update </strong>– Expanded analysis and threat intelligence from our continued monitoring of exploitation activity by <a href="#storm-2603">Storm-2603</a> leading to the deployment of Warlock ransomware. Based on new information, we have updated the <a href="#attribution">Attribution</a>, <a href="#indicators-of-compromise">Indicators of compromise</a>, extended and clarified <a href="#mitigation-and-protection-guidance">Mitigation and protection guidance</a> (including raising <em>Step 6: Restart IIS</em> for emphasis), <a href="#microsoft-defender-xdr-coverage">Detections</a>, and <a href="#hunting-queries">Hunting</a> sections.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">On July 19, 2025, Microsoft Security Response Center (MSRC) <a href="https://msrc.microsoft.com/blog/2025/07/customer-guidance-for-sharepoint-vulnerability-cve-2025-53770/">published a blog</a> addressing active attacks against on-premises SharePoint servers that exploit CVE-2025-49706, a spoofing vulnerability, and CVE-2025-49704, a remote code execution vulnerability. These vulnerabilities affect on-premises SharePoint servers only and do not affect SharePoint Online in Microsoft 365. Microsoft has released new comprehensive security updates for all supported versions of SharePoint Server (Subscription Edition, 2019, and 2016) that protect customers against these new vulnerabilities. Customers should apply these updates immediately to ensure they are protected.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">These comprehensive security updates address newly disclosed security vulnerabilities in <a href="https://msrc.microsoft.com/update-guide/vulnerability/CVE-2025-53770" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">CVE-2025-53770</a> that are related to the previously disclosed vulnerability CVE-2025-49704. The updates also address the security bypass vulnerability <a href="https://msrc.microsoft.com/update-guide/vulnerability/CVE-2025-53771">CVE-2025-53771</a> for the previously disclosed CVE-2025-49706.&nbsp;</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">As of this writing, Microsoft has observed two named Chinese nation-state actors, Linen Typhoon and Violet Typhoon exploiting these vulnerabilities targeting internet-facing SharePoint servers. In addition, we have observed another China-based threat actor, tracked as Storm-2603, exploiting these vulnerabilities to deploy ransomware. Investigations into other actors also using these exploits are still ongoing. With the rapid adoption of these exploits, Microsoft assesses with high confidence that threat actors will continue to integrate them into their attacks against unpatched on-premises SharePoint systems. This blog shares details of observed exploitation of CVE-2025-49706 and CVE-2025-49704 and the follow-on tactics, techniques, and procedures (TTPs) by threat actors. We will update this blog with more information as our investigation continues.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Microsoft recommends customers to use supported versions of on-premises SharePoint servers with the latest security updates. To stop unauthenticated attacks from exploiting this vulnerability, customers should also integrate and enable Antimalware Scan Interface (AMSI) and Microsoft Defender Antivirus (or equivalent solutions) for all on-premises SharePoint deployments and configure AMSI to enable Full Mode <a href="#mitigation-and-protection-guidance">as detailed in Mitigations section below</a>. Customers should also rotate SharePoint server ASP.NET machine keys, restart Internet Information Services (IIS), and deploy Microsoft Defender for Endpoint or equivalent solutions.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-table"><table class="has-fixed-layout"><tbody><tr><td><strong>Product</strong></td><td><strong>Security update link</strong></td></tr><tr><td>Microsoft SharePoint Server Subscription Edition</td><td><a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/download/details.aspx?id=108285">Security Update for Microsoft SharePoint Server Subscription Edition (KB5002768)</a></td></tr><tr><td>Microsoft SharePoint Server 2019 <em>(both updates should be installed)</em></td><td><a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/download/details.aspx?id=108286">Security Update for Microsoft SharePoint 2019 (KB5002754)</a> <br><br><a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/download/details.aspx?id=108287">Security Update for Microsoft SharePoint Server 2019 Language Pack (KB5002753)</a></td></tr><tr><td>Microsoft SharePoint Server 2016 <em>(both updates should be installed)</em></td><td><a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/download/details.aspx?id=108288">Security Update for Microsoft SharePoint Enterprise Server 2016 (KB5002760)</a> <br><br><a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/download/details.aspx?id=108289">Security Update for Microsoft SharePoint Enterprise Server 2016 Language Pack (KB5002759)</a></td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="observed-tactics-and-techniques">Observed tactics and techniques</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Microsoft observed multiple threat actors conducting reconnaissance and attempting exploitation of on-premises SharePoint servers through a POST request to the ToolPane endpoint.</p>


<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Fig1-Post-request-1024x171.webp" alt="A screenshot of a computer" class="wp-image-141370 webp-format" srcset="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Fig1-Post-request-1024x171.webp 1024w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Fig1-Post-request-300x50.webp 300w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Fig1-Post-request-768x128.webp 768w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Fig1-Post-request.webp 1113w" data-orig-src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Fig1-Post-request-1024x171.webp"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Figure 1. POST request to ToolPane endpoint</figcaption></figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="post-exploitation-activities">Post-exploitation activities</h3>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Threat actors who successfully executed the authentication bypass and remote code execution exploits against vulnerable on-premises SharePoint servers have been observed using a web shell in their post-exploitation payload.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="web-shell-deployment">Web shell deployment</h3>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">In observed attacks, threat actors send a crafted POST request to the SharePoint server, uploading a malicious script named <em>spinstall0.aspx.</em> Actors have also modified the file name in a variety of ways, such as <em>spinstall.aspx</em>, <em>spinstall1.aspx</em>, <em>spinstall2.aspx, </em>etc. The <em>spinstall0.aspx</em> script contains commands to retrieve MachineKey data and return the results to the user through a GET request, enabling the theft of the key material by threat actors.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="related-iocs-and-hunting-queries">Related IOCs and hunting queries</h3>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Microsoft provides indicators of compromise (IOCs) to identify and hunt for this web shell in the <a href="#indicators-of-compromise">Indicators of compromise</a> section of this blog. Microsoft provides related hunting queries to find this dropped file in the <a href="#hunting-queries">Hunting queries </a>section of this blog.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="attribution">Attribution</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">As early as July 7, 2025, Microsoft analysis suggests threat actors were attempting to exploit CVE-2025-49706 and CVE-2025-49704 to gain initial access to target organizations. These actors include Chinese state actors Linen Typhoon and Violet Typhoon and another China-based actor Storm-2603. &nbsp;The TTPs employed in these exploit attacks align with previously observed activities of these threat actors.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="linen-typhoon">Linen Typhoon</h3>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Since 2012, Linen Typhoon has focused on stealing intellectual property, primarily targeting organizations related to government, defense, strategic planning, and human rights. This threat actor is known for using drive-by compromises and historically has relied on existing exploits to compromise organizations.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="violet-typhoon">Violet Typhoon</h3>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Since 2015, the Violet Typhoon activity group has been dedicated to espionage, primarily targeting former government and military personnel, non-governmental organizations (NGOs), think tanks, higher education, digital and print media, financial and health related sectors in the United States, Europe, and East Asia. This group persistently scans for vulnerabilities in the exposed web infrastructure of target organizations, exploiting discovered weaknesses to install web shells.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="storm-2603">Storm-2603</h3>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">The group that Microsoft tracks as Storm-2603 is assessed with moderate confidence to be a China-based threat actor. Microsoft has not identified links between Storm-2603 and other known Chinese threat actors. Microsoft tracks this threat actor in association with attempts to steal MachineKeys using the on-premises SharePoint vulnerabilities. Although Microsoft has observed this threat actor deploying Warlock and Lockbit ransomware in the past, Microsoft is currently unable to confidently assess the threat actor’s objectives. Starting on July 18, 2025, Microsoft has observed Storm-2603 deploying ransomware using these vulnerabilities.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><strong>Initial access and delivery</strong></p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">The observed attack begins with the exploitation of an internet-facing on-premises SharePoint server, granting Storm-2603 initial access to the environment using the <em>spinstall0.aspx</em> payload described earlier in this blog. This initial access is used to conduct command execution using the w3wp.exe process that supports SharePoint. Storm-2603 then initiates a series of discovery commands, including <em>whoami</em>, to enumerate user context and validate privilege levels. The use of <em>cmd.exe</em> and batch scripts is also observed as the actor transitions into broader execution phases. Notably, <em>services.exe</em> is abused to disable Microsoft Defender protections through direct registry modifications.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><strong>Persistence</strong></p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Storm-2603 established persistence through multiple mechanisms. In addition to the <em>spinstall0.aspx</em> web shell, the threat actor also creates scheduled tasks and manipulates Internet Information Services (IIS) components to load suspicious .NET assemblies. These actions ensure continued access even if initial vectors are remediated.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><strong>Action on objectives</strong><strong></strong></p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">The threat actor performs credential access using Mimikatz, specifically targeting the Local Security Authority Subsystem Service (LSASS) memory to extract plaintext credentials. The actor moves laterally using PsExec and the Impacket toolkit, executing commands using Windows Management Instrumentation (WMI).</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Storm-2603 is then observed modifying Group Policy Objects (GPO) to distribute Warlock ransomware in compromised environments.</p>


<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Storm-2603-1024x601.webp" alt="A diagram of a computer" class="wp-image-141510 webp-format" srcset="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Storm-2603-1024x601.webp 1024w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Storm-2603-300x176.webp 300w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Storm-2603-768x451.webp 768w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Storm-2603-1536x901.webp 1536w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Storm-2603.webp 1742w" data-orig-src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Storm-2603-1024x601.webp"><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Figure 2. Storm-2603 attack chain exploiting SharePoint vulnerabilities and leading to ransomware</figcaption></figure>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><a id="_Mitigation_and_protection"></a>Additional actors will continue to use these exploits to target unpatched on-premises SharePoint systems, further emphasizing the need for organizations to implement mitigations and security updates immediately.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="mitigation-and-protection-guidance">Mitigation and protection guidance</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Microsoft has released security updates that fully protect customers using all supported versions of SharePoint affected by&nbsp;<a href="https://msrc.microsoft.com/update-guide/vulnerability/CVE-2025-53770" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">CVE-2025-53770</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="https://msrc.microsoft.com/update-guide/vulnerability/CVE-2025-53771" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">CVE-2025-53771</a>. Customers should apply these updates immediately.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Customers using SharePoint Server should follow the guidance below.</p>



<ol class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item"><strong>Use or upgrade to supported versions of on-premises Microsoft SharePoint Server.</strong>
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item">Supported versions: SharePoint Server 2016, 2019, and SharePoint Subscription Edition</li>
</ul>
</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item"><strong>Apply the latest security updates.</strong></li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item"><strong>Ensure the </strong><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/windows/win32/amsi/antimalware-scan-interface-portal"><strong>Antimalware Scan Interface</strong></a><strong> is turned on and configured correctly and deploy </strong><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/defender-endpoint/microsoft-defender-antivirus-on-windows-server"><strong>Defender Antivirus</strong></a><strong> on all SharePoint servers</strong>
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item">Configure <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/sharepoint/security-for-sharepoint-server/configure-amsi-integration">Antimalware Scan Interface</a>&nbsp;(AMSI) integration in SharePoint, enable <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/sharepoint/security-for-sharepoint-server/configure-amsi-integration#configure-amsi-via-user-interface">Full Mode</a> for optimal protection, and deploy <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/defender-endpoint/microsoft-defender-antivirus-on-windows-server">Defender Antivirus</a> on all SharePoint servers which will stop unauthenticated attackers from exploiting this vulnerability.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Note: AMSI integration was enabled by default in the September 2023 security update for SharePoint Server 2016/2019 and the Version 23H2 feature update for SharePoint Server Subscription Edition.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">If you cannot enable AMSI, we recommend you consider disconnecting your server from the internet until you have applied the most current security update linked above. If the server cannot be disconnected from the internet, consider using a VPN or proxy requiring authentication or an authentication gateway to limit unauthenticated traffic.</li>
</ul>
</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item"><strong>Deploy Microsoft Defender for Endpoint, or equivalent solutions</strong>
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item">We recommend organizations to deploy Defender for Endpoint to detect and block post-exploit activity.</li>
</ul>
</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item"><strong>Rotate SharePoint Server ASP.NET machine keys</strong>
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item">After applying the latest security updates above or enabling AMSI, it is critical that customers rotate SharePoint server ASP.NET machine keys and restart Internet Information Services (IIS) on all SharePoint servers.
<ol class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item">Manually using PowerShell
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item">To update the machine keys using PowerShell, use <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/sharepoint/security-for-sharepoint-server/improved-asp-net-view-state-security-key-management">the Set-SPMachineKey cmdlet</a>.</li>
</ul>
</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Manually using Central Admin: Trigger the Machine Key Rotation timer job by performing the following steps:
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item">Navigate to the&nbsp;<strong>Central Administration</strong>&nbsp;site.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Go to&nbsp;<strong>Monitoring</strong>&nbsp;-&gt;&nbsp;<strong>Review job definition</strong>.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Search for&nbsp;<strong>Machine Key Rotation Job</strong>&nbsp;and select&nbsp;<strong>Run Now</strong>.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
</li>
</ul>
</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item"><strong>Restart IIS on all SharePoint servers using <em>iisreset.exe</em>. </strong>NOTE: If you cannot enable AMSI, you will need to rotate your keys and restart IIS after you install the new security update.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item"><strong>Implement your incident response plan.</strong></li>
</ol>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">To protect against post-exploitation activity, including ransomware deployment, Microsoft recommends the following mitigations:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item">Turn on <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/microsoft-365/security/defender-endpoint/configure-block-at-first-sight-microsoft-defender-antivirus">cloud-delivered protection</a> in Microsoft Defender Antivirus or the equivalent for your antivirus product to cover rapidly evolving attacker tools and techniques. Cloud-based machine learning protections block a huge majority of new and unknown variants.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Read our <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/2022/05/09/ransomware-as-a-service-understanding-the-cybercrime-gig-economy-and-how-to-protect-yourself/#defending-against-ransomware">human-operated ransomware blog</a> for advice on developing a holistic security posture to prevent ransomware, including credential hygiene and hardening recommendations.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Run <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/defender-endpoint/edr-in-block-mode">endpoint detection and response (EDR) in block mode</a> so that Microsoft Defender for Endpoint – or equivalent EDR solution &#8211; can block malicious artifacts, even when your non-Microsoft antivirus does not detect the threat or when Microsoft Defender Antivirus is running in passive mode. EDR in block mode works behind the scenes to remediate malicious artifacts that are detected post-breach.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Configure <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/defender-xdr/configure-attack-disruption">automatic attack disruption</a> in Microsoft Defender XDR. Automatic attack disruption is designed to contain attacks in progress, limit the impact on an organization&#8217;s assets, and provide more time for security teams to remediate the attack fully.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item"><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/defender-endpoint/attack-surface-reduction-rules-reference#block-credential-stealing-from-the-windows-local-security-authority-subsystem">Enable</a> <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows-server/security/credentials-protection-and-management/configuring-additional-lsa-protection">LSA protection</a>.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Enable and configure <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/security/identity-protection/credential-guard/configure">Credential Guard</a>.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Ensure that <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/defender-endpoint/prevent-changes-to-security-settings-with-tamper-protection#how-do-i-configure-or-manage-tamper-protection">tamper protection</a> is enabled in Microsoft Defender for Endpoint.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Enable <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/defender-endpoint/enable-controlled-folders">controlled folder</a> access.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Microsoft Defender customers can turn on <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/defender-endpoint/attack-surface-reduction">attack surface reduction rules</a> to prevent common attack techniques. Attack surface reduction rules are sweeping settings that stop entire classes of threats. The following bullet points offer more guidance on specific mitigation advice:<ul><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/defender-endpoint/attack-surface-reduction-rules-reference?ocid=magicti_ta_learndoc#use-advanced-protection-against-ransomware">Use advanced protection against ransomware.</a></li></ul><ul><li><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/defender-endpoint/attack-surface-reduction-rules-reference#block-credential-stealing-from-the-windows-local-security-authority-subsystem">Block credential stealing from the Windows local security authority subsystem</a>.</li></ul>
<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item"><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/defender-endpoint/attack-surface-reduction-rules-reference?ocid=magicti_ta_learndoc#block-process-creations-originating-from-psexec-and-wmi-commands">Block process creations originating from PSExec and WMI commands</a>.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="indicators-of-compromise">Indicators of compromise</h2>



<figure class="wp-block-table"><table class="has-fixed-layout"><tbody><tr><td><strong>Indicator</strong></td><td><strong>Type</strong></td><td><strong>Description</strong></td></tr><tr><td><em>Spinstall0.aspx</em></td><td>File name</td><td>Web shell used by threat actors &nbsp; Actors have also modified the file name in a variety of ways &#8211; such as <em>spinstall.aspx</em>, <em>spinstall1.aspx</em>, <em>spinstall2.aspx</em></td></tr><tr><td><em>IIS_Server_dll.dll</em></td><td>File name</td><td>Storm-2603 IIS Backdoor</td></tr><tr><td><em>SharpHostInfo.x64.exe</em></td><td>File Name</td><td>Pentest tool observed during attack that is used to collect host information using NetBIOS, SMB, and WMI</td></tr><tr><td><em>xd.exe</em></td><td>File Name</td><td>Fast reverse proxy tool used to connect to C2 IP 65.38.121[.]198</td></tr><tr><td><em>debug_dev.js</em></td><td>File name</td><td>File containing web config data, including MachineKey data</td></tr><tr><td>\1[5-6]\TEMPLATE\LAYOUTS\debug_dev.js</td><td>File path</td><td>File path for stolen web configs</td></tr><tr><td>92bb4ddb98eeaf11fc15bb32e71d0a63256a0ed826a03ba293ce3a8bf057a514</td><td>SHA-256</td><td>Hash of <em>spinstall0.aspx</em></td></tr><tr><td>24480dbe306597da1ba393b6e30d542673066f98826cc07ac4b9033137f37dbf</td><td>SHA-256</td><td>Web shell that leverages http &amp; curl to receive and execute commands from Storm-2603 C2 “<em>update[.]updatemicfosoft[.]com”</em></td></tr><tr><td>b5a78616f709859a0d9f830d28ff2f9dbbb2387df1753739407917e96dadf6b0</td><td>SHA-256</td><td>Web shell that leverages sockets &amp; DNS to receive and execute commands from Storm-2603 C2 <em>“update[.]updatemicfosoft[.]com”</em></td></tr><tr><td>c27b725ff66fdfb11dd6487a3815d1d1eba89d61b0e919e4d06ed3ac6a74fe94</td><td>SHA-256</td><td>Web shell that leverages sockets &amp; DNS to receive and execute commands from Storm-2603 C2 <em>“update[.]updatemicfosoft[.]com”</em></td></tr><tr><td>1eb914c09c873f0a7bcf81475ab0f6bdfaccc6b63bf7e5f2dbf19295106af192</td><td>SHA-256</td><td>Web shell that leverages sockets &amp; DNS to receive and execute commands from Storm-2603 C2 <em>“update[.]updatemicfosoft[.]com”</em></td></tr><tr><td>4c1750a14915bf2c0b093c2cb59063912dfa039a2adfe6d26d6914804e2ae928</td><td>SHA-256</td><td>Observed hash for <em>IIS_Server_dll.dll </em>(Storm-2603 IIS Backdoor)</td></tr><tr><td>83705c75731e1d590b08f9357bc3b0f04741e92a033618736387512b40dab060</td><td>SHA-256</td><td>Observed hash for <em>IIS_Server_dll.dll </em>(Storm-2603 IIS Backdoor)</td></tr><tr><td>f54ae00a9bae73da001c4d3d690d26ddf5e8e006b5562f936df472ec5e299441</td><td>SHA-256</td><td>Observed hash for <em>IIS_Server_dll.dll </em>(Storm-2603 IIS Backdoor)</td></tr><tr><td>b180ab0a5845ed619939154f67526d2b04d28713fcc1904fbd666275538f431d</td><td>SHA-256</td><td>Observed hash for <em>IIS_Server_dll.dll </em>(Storm-2603 IIS Backdoor)</td></tr><tr><td>6753b840cec65dfba0d7d326ec768bff2495784c60db6a139f51c5e83349ac4d</td><td>SHA-256</td><td>Observed hash for <em>IIS_Server_dll.dll </em>(Storm-2603 IIS Backdoor)</td></tr><tr><td>7ae971e40528d364fa52f3bb5e0660ac25ef63e082e3bbd54f153e27b31eae68</td><td>SHA-256</td><td>Observed hash for <em>IIS_Server_dll.dll </em>(Storm-2603 IIS Backdoor)</td></tr><tr><td>567cb8e8c8bd0d909870c656b292b57bcb24eb55a8582b884e0a228e298e7443</td><td>SHA-256</td><td>Observed hash for <em>IIS_Server_dll.dll </em>(Storm-2603 IIS Backdoor)</td></tr><tr><td>445a37279d3a229ed18513e85f0c8d861c6f560e0f914a5869df14a74b679b86</td><td>SHA-256</td><td>Observed hash for <em>IIS_Server_dll.dll </em>(Storm-2603 IIS Backdoor)</td></tr><tr><td>ffbc9dfc284b147e07a430fe9471e66c716a84a1f18976474a54bee82605fa9a</td><td>SHA-256</td><td>Observed hash for <em>IIS_Server_dll.dll </em>(Storm-2603 IIS Backdoor)</td></tr><tr><td>6b273c2179518dacb1218201fd37ee2492a5e1713be907e69bf7ea56ceca53a5</td><td>SHA-256</td><td>Observed hash for <em>IIS_Server_dll.dll </em>(Storm-2603 IIS Backdoor)</td></tr><tr><td>c2c1fec7856e8d49f5d49267e69993837575dbbec99cd702c5be134a85b2c139</td><td>SHA-256</td><td>Observed hash for <em>IIS_Server_dll.dll </em>(Storm-2603 IIS Backdoor)</td></tr><tr><td>6f6db63ece791c6dc1054f1e1231b5bbcf6c051a49bad0784569271753e24619</td><td>SHA-256</td><td>Observed hash for <em>IIS_Server_dll.dll </em>(Storm-2603 IIS Backdoor)</td></tr><tr><td>d6da885c90a5d1fb88d0a3f0b5d9817a82d5772d5510a0773c80ca581ce2486d</td><td>SHA-256</td><td>Hash for <em>SharpHostInfo.x64.exe</em></td></tr><tr><td>62881359e75c9e8899c4bc9f452ef9743e68ce467f8b3e4398bebacde9550dea</td><td>SHA-256</td><td>Hash for <em>xd.exe</em></td></tr><tr><td><em>c34718cbb4c6.ngrok-free[.]app/file.ps1</em></td><td>URL</td><td>Ngrok tunnel delivering PowerShell to C2</td></tr><tr><td>msupdate[.]updatemicfosoft[.]com</td><td>URL</td><td>C2 domain for Storm-2603</td></tr><tr><td>131.226.2[.]6</td><td>IP</td><td>Post exploitation C2</td></tr><tr><td>134.199.202[.]205</td><td>IP</td><td>IP address exploiting SharePoint vulnerabilities</td></tr><tr><td>104.238.159[.]149</td><td>IP</td><td>IP address exploiting SharePoint vulnerabilities</td></tr><tr><td>188.130.206[.]168</td><td>IP</td><td>IP address exploiting SharePoint vulnerabilities</td></tr><tr><td>65.38.121[.]198</td><td>IP</td><td>Post-exploitation C2 for Storm-2603</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="microsoft-defender-xdr-coverage">Microsoft Defender XDR coverage</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Microsoft Defender XDR customers get coordinated protection across endpoints, identities, email, and cloud apps to detect, prevent, investigate, and respond to threats like the SharePoint exploitation activity described in this blog.&nbsp;</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Customers with provisioned access can also use <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/defender-xdr/security-copilot-in-microsoft-365-defender">Microsoft Security Copilot in Microsoft Defender</a> to investigate and respond to incidents, hunt for threats, and protect their organization with relevant threat intelligence.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">The following table outlines the tactics observed in the exploitation attacks discussed in this blog, along with Microsoft Defender protection coverage at each stage of the attack chain:&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-table"><table class="has-fixed-layout"><tbody><tr><td><strong>Tactic&nbsp;</strong><strong></strong></td><td><strong>Observed activity&nbsp;</strong><strong></strong></td><td><strong>Microsoft Defender coverage&nbsp;</strong><strong></strong></td></tr><tr><td>Initial Access&nbsp;</td><td>Use of known vulnerabilities to exploit internet-facing SharePoint servers&nbsp;</td><td><strong>Microsoft Defender Antivirus</strong><br>-Exploit:Script/SuspSignoutReq.A <br>&#8211; Exploit:Script/SuspSignoutReqBody.A  <br><strong>Microsoft Defender for Endpoint</strong> <br>&#8211; &#8216;SuspSignoutReq&#8217; malware was blocked on a SharePoint server <br>&#8211; Possible exploitation of SharePoint server vulnerabilities </td></tr><tr><td>Execution&nbsp;</td><td>Use of a web shell to run PowerShell and exfiltrate sensitive data (e.g., MachineKey); Batch scripts and <em>cmd.exe</em> to launch PsExec for remote execution; Attempts to disable Microsoft Defender protections through registry edits using the service control manager; Escalation of privileges to SYSTEM using PsExec with the <em>-s</em> flag; Use of Impacket to execute commands remotely over WMI without writing files to disk</td><td><strong>Microsoft Defender Antivirus </strong> <br>&#8211; Trojan:Win32/HijackSharePointServer.A <br><strong>Microsoft Defender for Endpoint </strong> <br>&#8211; Suspicious IIS worker process behavior  &#8211; Suspicious scheduled task &#8211; Impacket toolkit</td></tr><tr><td>Persistence&nbsp;</td><td>Installation of web shell after exploiting SharePoint vulnerability; IIS worker process loaded suspicious .NET assembly; Scheduled task&nbsp; for persistence following initial access</td><td><strong>Microsoft Defender Antivirus </strong> <br>&#8211; Trojan:PowerShell/MachineKeyFinder.DA!amsi  <br><strong>Microsoft Defender for Endpoint </strong> <br>&#8211; Possible web shell installation &#8211; IIS worker process loaded suspicious .NET assembly</td></tr><tr><td>Credential Access</td><td>Mimikatz used to run module &#8220;sekurlsa::logonpasswords&#8221;, which lists all available credentials</td><td><strong>Microsoft Defender for Endpoint</strong> <br>&#8211; Mimikatz credential theft tool</td></tr><tr><td>Lateral Movement</td><td>Impacket is observed leveraging Windows Management Instrumentation to remotely stage and execute payloads</td><td><strong>Microsoft Defender for Endpoint</strong> <br>&#8211; A remote resource was accessed suspiciously <br>&#8211; Compromised account conducting hands-on-keyboard attack <br>&#8211; Ongoing hands-on-keyboard attack via Impacket toolkit</td></tr><tr><td>Collection&nbsp;</td><td>Web shell used to extract MachineKey data&nbsp;</td><td><strong>Microsoft Defender Antivirus </strong> <br>&#8211; Trojan:PowerShell/MachineKeyFinder.DA!amsi <br><strong>Microsoft Defender for Endpoint </strong> <br>&#8211; Possible web shell installation</td></tr><tr><td>Impact</td><td>Files encrypted in compromised environments as part of ransomware attack</td><td><strong>Microsoft Defender for Endpoint</strong> <br>&#8211; Ransomware-linked threat actor detected <br>&#8211; Potentially compromised assets exhibiting ransomware-like behavior <br>&#8211; Ransomware behavior detected in the file system <br>&#8211; Possible compromised user account delivering ransomware-related file <br>&#8211; Potential human-operated malicious activity</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Note: These alerts can also be triggered by unrelated threat activity&nbsp;</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="vulnerability-management">Vulnerability management</h3>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Customers using Microsoft Defender Vulnerability Management can identify exposed devices and track remediation efforts based on the following CVEs:&nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item">CVE-2025-53770 – SharePoint ToolShell Auth Bypass and RCE&nbsp;</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">CVE-2025-53771 – SharePoint ToolShell Path Traversal&nbsp;</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">CVE-2025-49704 – SharePoint RCE&nbsp;</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">CVE-2025-49706 – SharePoint Post-auth RCE&nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Navigate to <strong>Vulnerability management</strong> ><strong> Weaknesses </strong>and filter by these CVE IDs to view exposed devices, remediation status, and <em>Evidence of Exploitation</em> tags.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">You can also use this unified advanced hunting query:</p>


<div class="wp-block-syntaxhighlighter-code "><pre class="brush: plain; auto-links: false; gutter: false; title: ; quick-code: false; notranslate">
DeviceTvmSoftwareVulnerabilities 
| where CveId in ( 
    "CVE-2025-49704", 
    "CVE-2025-49706", 
    "CVE-2025-53770", 
    "CVE-2025-53771") 
</pre></div>


<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="external-attack-surface-management-defender-easm">External Attack Surface Management (Defender EASM)&nbsp;</h3>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Microsoft Defender External Attack Surface Management (Defender EASM) provides visibility into exposed internet-facing SharePoint instances. The following Attack Surface Insights may indicate vulnerable but not necessarily exploited services:&nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item">CVE-2025-49704 – SharePoint RCE&nbsp;</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">CVE-2025-53770 – SharePoint ToolShell Auth Bypass and RCE&nbsp;</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">CVE-2025-53771 – SharePoint ToolShell Path Traversal&nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Note: A “Potential” insight signals that a service is detected but version validation is not possible. Customers should manually verify patching status.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="hunting-queries">Hunting queries</h2>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="microsoft-defender-xdr">Microsoft Defender XDR</h3>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">To locate possible exploitation activity, run the following queries in Microsoft Defender XDR security center.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><strong>Successful exploitation using file creation</strong>  </p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Look for the creation of <em>spinstall0.aspx</em>, which indicates successful post-exploitation of CVE-2025-53770.&nbsp;</p>


<div class="wp-block-syntaxhighlighter-code "><pre class="brush: plain; auto-links: false; gutter: false; title: ; quick-code: false; notranslate">
DeviceFileEvents 
| where FolderPath has_any ("microsoft shared\\Web Server Extensions\\15\\TEMPLATE\\LAYOUTS", "microsoft shared\\Web Server Extensions\\16\\TEMPLATE\\LAYOUTS") 
| where FileName contains "spinstall"
| project Timestamp, DeviceName, InitiatingProcessFileName, InitiatingProcessCommandLine, FileName, FolderPath, ReportId, ActionType, SHA256 
| order by Timestamp desc
</pre></div>


<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><strong>Post-exploitation PowerShell dropping web shell</strong></p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Look for process creation where <em>w3wp.exe</em> is spawning encoded PowerShell involving the <em>spinstall0.aspx</em> file or the file paths it’s been known to be written to.</p>


<div class="wp-block-syntaxhighlighter-code "><pre class="brush: plain; auto-links: false; gutter: false; title: ; quick-code: false; notranslate">
DeviceProcessEvents
| where InitiatingProcessFileName has "w3wp.exe"
    and InitiatingProcessCommandLine !has "DefaultAppPool"
    and FileName =~ "cmd.exe"
    and ProcessCommandLine has_all ("cmd.exe", "powershell")
    and ProcessCommandLine has_any ("EncodedCommand", "-ec")
| extend CommandArguments = split(ProcessCommandLine, " ")
| mv-expand CommandArguments to typeof(string)
| where CommandArguments matches regex "^&#x5B;A-Za-z0-9+/=]{15,}$"
| extend B64Decode = replace("\\x00", "", base64_decodestring(tostring(CommandArguments)))   
| where B64Decode contains "spinstall", @'C:\PROGRA~1\COMMON~1\MICROS~1\WEBSER~1\15\TEMPLATE\LAYOUTS', @'C:\PROGRA~1\COMMON~1\MICROS~1\WEBSER~1\16\TEMPLATE\LAYOUTS')
</pre></div>


<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><strong>Post-exploitation web shell dropped</strong></p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Look for the web shell dropped using the PowerShell command.</p>


<div class="wp-block-syntaxhighlighter-code "><pre class="brush: plain; auto-links: false; gutter: false; title: ; quick-code: false; notranslate">
DeviceFileEvents
| where Timestamp &gt;ago(7d)
| where InitiatingProcessFileName=~&quot;powershell.exe&quot;
| where FileName contains &quot;spinstall&quot;
</pre></div>


<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><strong>Exploitation detected by Defender</strong></p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Look at Microsoft Defender for Endpoint telemetry to determine if specific alerts fired in your environment.</p>


<div class="wp-block-syntaxhighlighter-code "><pre class="brush: plain; auto-links: false; gutter: false; title: ; quick-code: false; notranslate">
AlertEvidence 
| where Timestamp &gt; ago(7d) 
| where Title has &quot;SuspSignoutReq&quot; 
| extend _DeviceKey = iff(isnotempty(DeviceId), bag_pack_columns(DeviceId, DeviceName),&quot;&quot;) 
| summarize min(Timestamp), max(Timestamp), count_distinctif(DeviceId,isnotempty(DeviceId)), make_set(Title), make_set_if(_DeviceKey, isnotempty(_DeviceKey) )
</pre></div>


<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="unified-advanced-hunting-queries">Unified advanced hunting queries</h3>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><strong>Find exposed devices</strong></p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Look for devices vulnerable to the CVEs listed in blog.</p>


<div class="wp-block-syntaxhighlighter-code "><pre class="brush: plain; auto-links: false; gutter: false; title: ; quick-code: false; notranslate">
DeviceTvmSoftwareVulnerabilities 
| where CveId in ("CVE-2025-49704","CVE-2025-49706","CVE-2025-53770","CVE-2025-53771") 
</pre></div>


<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><strong>Web shell C2 communication</strong></p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Find devices that may have communicated with Storm-2603 web shell C2, that may indicate a compromised device beaconing to Storm-2603 controlled infrastructure.</p>


<div class="wp-block-syntaxhighlighter-code "><pre class="brush: plain; auto-links: false; gutter: false; title: ; quick-code: false; notranslate">
let domainList = "update.updatemicfosoft.com";
union
(
    DnsEvents
    | where QueryType has_any(domainList) or Name has_any(domainList) or QueryType matches regex @"^.*\.devtunnels\.ms$" or Name matches regex @"^.*\.devtunnels\.ms$"
    | project TimeGenerated, Domain = QueryType, SourceTable = "DnsEvents"
),
(
    IdentityQueryEvents
    | where QueryTarget has_any(domainList) or QueryType matches regex @"^.*\.devtunnels\.ms$"
    | project Timestamp, Domain = QueryTarget, SourceTable = "IdentityQueryEvents"
),
(
    DeviceNetworkEvents
    | where RemoteUrl has_any(domainList) or RemoteUrl matches regex @"^.*\.devtunnels\.ms$"
    | project Timestamp, Domain = RemoteUrl, SourceTable = "DeviceNetworkEvents"
),
(
    DeviceNetworkInfo
    | extend DnsAddresses = parse_json(DnsAddresses), ConnectedNetworks = parse_json(ConnectedNetworks)
    | mv-expand DnsAddresses, ConnectedNetworks
    | where DnsAddresses has_any(domainList) or ConnectedNetworks.Name has_any(domainList) or DnsAddresses matches regex @"^.*\.devtunnels\.ms$" or ConnectedNetworks .Name matches regex @"^.*\.devtunnels\.ms$"
    | project Timestamp, Domain = coalesce(DnsAddresses, ConnectedNetworks.Name), SourceTable = "DeviceNetworkInfo"
),
(
    VMConnection
    | extend RemoteDnsQuestions = parse_json(RemoteDnsQuestions), RemoteDnsCanonicalNames = parse_json(RemoteDnsCanonicalNames)
    | mv-expand RemoteDnsQuestions, RemoteDnsCanonicalNames
    | where RemoteDnsQuestions has_any(domainList) or RemoteDnsCanonicalNames has_any(domainList) or RemoteDnsQuestions matches regex @"^.*\.devtunnels\.ms$" or RemoteDnsCanonicalNames matches regex @"^.*\.devtunnels\.ms$"
    | project TimeGenerated, Domain = coalesce(RemoteDnsQuestions, RemoteDnsCanonicalNames), SourceTable = "VMConnection"
),
(
    W3CIISLog
    | where csHost has_any(domainList) or csReferer has_any(domainList) or csHost matches regex @"^.*\.devtunnels\.ms$" or csReferer matches regex @"^.*\.devtunnels\.ms$"
    | project TimeGenerated, Domain = coalesce(csHost, csReferer), SourceTable = "W3CIISLog"
),
(
    EmailUrlInfo
    | where UrlDomain has_any(domainList) or UrlDomain matches regex @"^.*\.devtunnels\.ms$"
    | project Timestamp, Domain = UrlDomain, SourceTable = "EmailUrlInfo"
),
(
    UrlClickEvents
    | where Url has_any(domainList) or Url matches regex @"^.*\.devtunnels\.ms$"
    | project Timestamp, Domain = Url, SourceTable = "UrlClickEvents"
)
| order by TimeGenerated desc
</pre></div>


<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="microsoft-sentinel">Microsoft Sentinel</h3>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Microsoft Sentinel customers can use the TI Mapping analytics (a series of analytics all prefixed with ‘TI map’) to automatically match the malicious domain indicators mentioned in this blog post with data in their workspace. If the TI Map analytics are not currently deployed, customers can install the Threat Intelligence solution from the&nbsp;<a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/azure/sentinel/sentinel-solutions-deploy">Microsoft Sentinel Content Hub</a>&nbsp;to have the analytics rule deployed in their Sentinel workspace.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Our post on&nbsp;<a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/t5/microsoft-sentinel-blog/web-shell-threat-hunting-with-azure-sentinel/ba-p/2234968">web shell threat hunting with Microsoft Sentinel&nbsp;</a>also provides guidance on looking for web shells in general.&nbsp;Several hunting queries are also available below:&nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item"><a href="https://github.com/Azure/Azure-Sentinel/blob/master/Solutions/Web%20Shells%20Threat%20Protection/Hunting%20Queries/PotentialWebshell.yaml">Web shell detection</a></li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item"><a href="https://github.com/Azure/Azure-Sentinel/blob/master/Solutions/Web%20Shells%20Threat%20Protection/Hunting%20Queries/Possible%20webshell%20drop.yaml">Possible Webshell drop</a></li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item"><a href="https://github.com/Azure/Azure-Sentinel/blob/master/Solutions/Web%20Shells%20Threat%20Protection/Analytic%20Rules/MaliciousAlertLinkedWebRequests.yaml">Malicious web application requests linked with Microsoft Defender for Endpoint alerts</a>&nbsp;</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item"><a href="https://github.com/Azure/Azure-Sentinel/blob/master/Solutions/Web%20Shells%20Threat%20Protection/Hunting%20Queries/WebShellActivity.yaml">Web shell activity</a>&nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Below are the queries using&nbsp;<a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/azure/sentinel/normalization">Sentinel Advanced Security Information Model (ASIM) functions</a>&nbsp;to hunt threats across both Microsoft first-party and third-party data sources. ASIM also supports deploying parsers to specific workspaces&nbsp;<a href="https://aka.ms/DeployASIM">from GitHub</a>, using an ARM template or manually.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><strong>Detect network indicators of compromise and file hashes using ASIM</strong></p>


<div class="wp-block-syntaxhighlighter-code "><pre class="brush: plain; auto-links: false; gutter: false; title: ; quick-code: false; notranslate">
//IP list and domain list- _Im_NetworkSession
let lookback = 30d;
let ioc_ip_addr = dynamic(&#x5B;"131.226.2.6", "134.199.202.205", "104.238.159.149", "188.130.206.168"]);
let ioc_domains = dynamic(&#x5B;"c34718cbb4c6.ngrok-free.app"]);
_Im_NetworkSession(starttime=todatetime(ago(lookback)), endtime=now())
| where DstIpAddr in (ioc_ip_addr) or DstDomain has_any (ioc_domains)
| summarize imNWS_mintime=min(TimeGenerated), imNWS_maxtime=max(TimeGenerated),
  EventCount=count() by SrcIpAddr, DstIpAddr, DstDomain, Dvc, EventProduct, EventVendor
</pre></div>

<div class="wp-block-syntaxhighlighter-code "><pre class="brush: plain; auto-links: false; gutter: false; title: ; quick-code: false; notranslate">
//IP list - _Im_WebSession
let lookback = 30d;
let ioc_ip_addr = dynamic(&#x5B;"131.226.2.6", "134.199.202.205", "104.238.159.149", "188.130.206.168"]);
let ioc_sha_hashes =dynamic(&#x5B;"92bb4ddb98eeaf11fc15bb32e71d0a63256a0ed826a03ba293ce3a8bf057a514"]);
_Im_WebSession(starttime=todatetime(ago(lookback)), endtime=now())
| where DstIpAddr in (ioc_ip_addr) or FileSHA256 in (ioc_sha_hashes)
| summarize imWS_mintime=min(TimeGenerated), imWS_maxtime=max(TimeGenerated),
  EventCount=count() by SrcIpAddr, DstIpAddr, Url, Dvc, EventProduct, EventVendor
</pre></div>

<div class="wp-block-syntaxhighlighter-code "><pre class="brush: plain; auto-links: false; gutter: false; title: ; quick-code: false; notranslate">
// file hash list - imFileEvent
let ioc_sha_hashes = dynamic(&#x5B;"92bb4ddb98eeaf11fc15bb32e71d0a63256a0ed826a03ba293ce3a8bf057a514"]);
imFileEvent
| where SrcFileSHA256 in (ioc_sha_hashes) or TargetFileSHA256 in (ioc_sha_hashes)
| extend AccountName = tostring(split(User, @'')&#x5B;1]), 
  AccountNTDomain = tostring(split(User, @'')&#x5B;0])
| extend AlgorithmType = "SHA256"
</pre></div>


<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><strong>Post exploitation C2 or file hashes</strong><strong></strong></p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Find devices that may have communicated with Storm-2603 post exploitation C2 or contain known Storm-2603 file hashes.</p>


<div class="wp-block-syntaxhighlighter-code "><pre class="brush: plain; auto-links: false; gutter: false; title: ; quick-code: false; notranslate">
//IP list - _Im_WebSession
let lookback = 30d;
let ioc_ip_addr = dynamic(&#x5B;"65.38.121.198"]);
let ioc_sha_hashes =dynamic(&#x5B;"92bb4ddb98eeaf11fc15bb32e71d0a63256a0ed826a03ba293ce3a8bf057a514", 
"24480dbe306597da1ba393b6e30d542673066f98826cc07ac4b9033137f37dbf", 
"b5a78616f709859a0d9f830d28ff2f9dbbb2387df1753739407917e96dadf6b0", 
"c27b725ff66fdfb11dd6487a3815d1d1eba89d61b0e919e4d06ed3ac6a74fe94", 
"1eb914c09c873f0a7bcf81475ab0f6bdfaccc6b63bf7e5f2dbf19295106af192", 
"4c1750a14915bf2c0b093c2cb59063912dfa039a2adfe6d26d6914804e2ae928", 
"83705c75731e1d590b08f9357bc3b0f04741e92a033618736387512b40dab060", 
"f54ae00a9bae73da001c4d3d690d26ddf5e8e006b5562f936df472ec5e299441", 
"b180ab0a5845ed619939154f67526d2b04d28713fcc1904fbd666275538f431d", 
"6753b840cec65dfba0d7d326ec768bff2495784c60db6a139f51c5e83349ac4d", 
"7ae971e40528d364fa52f3bb5e0660ac25ef63e082e3bbd54f153e27b31eae68", 
"567cb8e8c8bd0d909870c656b292b57bcb24eb55a8582b884e0a228e298e7443", 
"445a37279d3a229ed18513e85f0c8d861c6f560e0f914a5869df14a74b679b86", 
"ffbc9dfc284b147e07a430fe9471e66c716a84a1f18976474a54bee82605fa9a", 
"6b273c2179518dacb1218201fd37ee2492a5e1713be907e69bf7ea56ceca53a5", 
"c2c1fec7856e8d49f5d49267e69993837575dbbec99cd702c5be134a85b2c139"]);
_Im_WebSession(starttime=todatetime(ago(lookback)), endtime=now())
| where DstIpAddr in (ioc_ip_addr) or FileSHA256 in (ioc_sha_hashes)
| summarize imWS_mintime=min(TimeGenerated), imWS_maxtime=max(TimeGenerated),
  EventCount=count() by SrcIpAddr, DstIpAddr, Url, Dvc, EventProduct, EventVendor
</pre></div>


<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><strong>Storm-2603 C2 communication</strong><strong></strong></p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Look for devices that may have communicated with Storm-2603 C2 infrastructure as part of this activity.</p>


<div class="wp-block-syntaxhighlighter-code "><pre class="brush: plain; auto-links: false; gutter: false; title: ; quick-code: false; notranslate">
//IP list and domain list- _Im_NetworkSession
let lookback = 30d;
let ioc_ip_addr = dynamic(&#x5B;"65.38.121.198"]);
let ioc_domains = dynamic(&#x5B;"update.updatemicfosoft.com"]);
_Im_NetworkSession(starttime=todatetime(ago(lookback)), endtime=now())
| where DstIpAddr in (ioc_ip_addr) or DstDomain has_any (ioc_domains)
| summarize imNWS_mintime=min(TimeGenerated), imNWS_maxtime=max(TimeGenerated),
  EventCount=count() by SrcIpAddr, DstIpAddr, DstDomain, Dvc, EventProduct, EventVendor
</pre></div>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="microsoft-security-copilot">Microsoft Security Copilot</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Microsoft Security Copilot customers can use the standalone experience to <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/copilot/security/prompting-security-copilot#create-your-own-prompts">create their own prompts</a> or run the following <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/copilot/security/using-promptbooks">prebuilt promptbooks</a> to automate incident response or investigation tasks related to this threat:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item">Vulnerability impact assessment</li>
</ul>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Note that some promptbooks require access to plugins for Microsoft products such as Microsoft Defender XDR or Microsoft Sentinel.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="threat-intelligence-reports">Threat intelligence reports</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Microsoft customers can use the following reports in Microsoft products to get the most up-to-date information about the threat actor, malicious activity, and techniques discussed in this blog. These reports provide the intelligence, protection information, and recommended actions to prevent, mitigate, or respond to associated threats found in customer environments.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="microsoft-defender-threat-intelligence">Microsoft Defender Threat Intelligence</h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item"><a href="https://security.microsoft.com/intel-profiles/CVE-2025-53770">CVE-2025-53770 – Microsoft SharePoint server remote code execution vulnerability</a></li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item"><a href="https://security.microsoft.com/intel-explorer/articles/93e1c483">Storm-2603 exploiting on-premises SharePoint vulnerabilities to distribute Warlock ransomware</a></li>
</ul>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Microsoft Security Copilot customers can also use the <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/defender/threat-intelligence/security-copilot-and-defender-threat-intelligence?bc=%2Fsecurity-copilot%2Fbreadcrumb%2Ftoc.json&amp;toc=%2Fsecurity-copilot%2Ftoc.json#turn-on-the-security-copilot-integration-in-defender-ti">Microsoft Security Copilot integration</a> in Microsoft Defender Threat Intelligence, either in the Security Copilot standalone portal or in the <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/defender/threat-intelligence/using-copilot-threat-intelligence-defender-xdr">embedded experience</a> in the Microsoft Defender portal to get more information about this threat actor.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="mitre-att-ck-techniques-observed"><a></a>MITRE ATT&amp;CK techniques observed&nbsp;</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Threat actors have exhibited use of the following attack techniques. For standard industry documentation about these techniques, refer to the <a href="https://attack.mitre.org/">MITRE ATT&amp;CK framework</a>.&nbsp;</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><strong>Initial Access</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item"><a href="https://attack.mitre.org/techniques/T1190/">T1190 Exploit public-facing application</a> | Use of known vulnerabilities to exploit internet-facing on-premises SharePoint severs </li>
</ul>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><strong>Discovery</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item"><a href="https://attack.mitre.org/techniques/T1033/">T1033 System Owner/User Discovery</a> | Whoami commands run after initial access and privilege escalation</li>
</ul>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><strong>Execution</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item"><a href="https://attack.mitre.org/techniques/T1059/001/">T1059.001 Command and scripting interpreter: PowerShell</a> | Use of a web shell to run PowerShell to read and transmit MachineKey data to attacker</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item"><a href="https://attack.mitre.org/techniques/T1059/003/">T1059.003 Command and Scripting Interpreter: Windows Command Shell</a> | Use of batch scripts and <em>cmd.exe</em> to execute PsExec</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item"><a href="https://attack.mitre.org/techniques/T1569/002/">T1569.002 System Services: Service Execution</a> | Windows service control manager is abused to disable Microsoft Defender protections through registry modifications and launch PsExec</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item"><a href="https://attack.mitre.org/techniques/T1543/003/">T1543.003 Create or Modify System Process: Windows Service</a> | PsExec is leveraged Windows services to escalate privileges from administrator to SYSTEM with the <em>-s</em> argument</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item"><a href="https://attack.mitre.org/techniques/T1047/">T1047 Windows Management Instrumentation</a> | Impacket is used to execute commands through WMI</li>
</ul>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><strong>Persistence</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item"><a href="https://attack.mitre.org/techniques/T1505/003/">T1505.003 Server software component: web shell</a> | Threat actors install web shell after exploiting SharePoint vulnerability</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item"><a href="https://attack.mitre.org/techniques/T1505/004/">T1505.004 Server Software Component: IIS Components</a> | IIS worker process is loaded suspicious .NET assembly</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item"><a href="https://attack.mitre.org/techniques/T1053/005/">T1053.005 Scheduled Task/Job: Scheduled Task</a> | Scheduled task is created to maintain persistence following initial access</li>
</ul>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><strong>Privilege Escalation</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item"><a href="https://attack.mitre.org/techniques/T1484/001/">T1484.001 Domain or Tenant Policy Modification: Group Policy Modification</a> | GPO modification deployed batch scripts for ransomware deployment</li>
</ul>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><strong>Defense Evasion</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item"><a href="https://attack.mitre.org/techniques/T1620/">T1620 Reflective code loading</a> | Reflectively loaded payloads</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item"><a href="https://attack.mitre.org/techniques/T1562/001/">T1562.001 Impair Defenses: Disable or Modify Tools</a> | Disabling Microsoft Defender via registry modifications</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item"><a href="https://attack.mitre.org/techniques/T1112/">T1112 Modify Registry</a> | Disabling Microsoft Defender via registry modifications</li>
</ul>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><strong>Credential Access</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item"><a href="https://attack.mitre.org/techniques/T1003/001/">T1003.001 OS Credential Dumping: LSASS Memory</a> | Mimikatz is used to run module <em>sekurlsa::logonpasswords</em>, which lists all available credentials</li>
</ul>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><strong>Lateral Movement</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item"><a href="https://attack.mitre.org/techniques/T1570/">T1570 Lateral Tool Transfer</a> | Impacket is observed leveraging Windows Management Instrumentation to remotely stage and execute payloads</li>
</ul>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><strong>Collection</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item"><a href="https://attack.mitre.org/techniques/T1119/">T1119 Automated collection</a> | Use of web shell to display MachineKey data</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item"><a href="https://attack.mitre.org/techniques/T1005/">T1005 Data from Local System</a> | Host and local system information gathered by adversary during attack</li>
</ul>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><strong>Command and Control</strong><strong></strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item"><a href="https://attack.mitre.org/techniques/T1090/">T1090 Proxy, Technique</a> | Fast reverse proxy tool used for C2 communications</li>
</ul>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><strong>Impact</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item"><a href="https://attack.mitre.org/techniques/T1486/">T1486 Data Encrypted for Impact</a> | Files are encrypted in victim environments as part of ransomware attack</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="references">References</h2>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item"><a href="https://msrc.microsoft.com/update-guide/vulnerability/CVE-2025-53770">CVE-2025-53770</a> (MSRC) </li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item"><a href="https://msrc.microsoft.com/update-guide/vulnerability/CVE-2025-49704">CVE-2025-49704</a> (MSRC</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item"><a href="https://msrc.microsoft.com/update-guide/vulnerability/CVE-2025-49706">CVE-2025-49706</a> (MSRC</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item"><a href="https://msrc.microsoft.com/update-guide/vulnerability/CVE-2025-53771">CVE-2025-53771</a> (MSRC)</li>
</ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="learn-more">Learn more</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Meet the experts behind Microsoft Threat Intelligence, Incident Response, and the Microsoft Security Response Center at our <a href="https://microsoftsecurityevents.eventbuilder.com/events/11f048838dabd650892acff3dd777035?ref=blog">VIP Mixer at Black Hat 2025</a>. Discover how our end-to-end platform can help you strengthen resilience and elevate your security posture.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">For the latest security research from the Microsoft Threat Intelligence community, check out the <a href="https://aka.ms/threatintelblog">Microsoft Threat Intelligence Blog</a>.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">To get notified about new publications and to join discussions on social media, follow us on <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/showcase/microsoft-threat-intelligence">LinkedIn</a>, <a href="https://x.com/MsftSecIntel">X (formerly Twitter)</a>, and <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/threatintel.microsoft.com">Bluesky</a>.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">To hear stories and insights from the Microsoft Threat Intelligence community about the ever-evolving threat landscape, listen to the <a href="https://thecyberwire.com/podcasts/microsoft-threat-intelligence">Microsoft Threat Intelligence podcast</a>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/2025/07/22/disrupting-active-exploitation-of-on-premises-sharepoint-vulnerabilities/">Disrupting active exploitation of on-premises SharePoint vulnerabilities</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog">Microsoft Security Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Microsoft Sentinel data lake: Unify signals, cut costs, and power agentic AI</title>
		<link>https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/2025/07/22/microsoft-sentinel-data-lake-unify-signals-cut-costs-and-power-agentic-ai/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Scott Woodgate and Krishna Kumar Parthasarathy]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/?p=139298</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>We’re evolving our industry-leading Security Incidents and Event Management solution (SIEM), Microsoft Sentinel, to include a modern, cost-effective data lake. By unifying all your security data, Microsoft Sentinel data lake, in public preview, accelerates AI adoption and drives unparalleled visibility, empowering teams to detect and respond faster. With Sentinel data lake, you’re no longer forced to choose between retaining critical data and staying within budget. ​ </p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/2025/07/22/microsoft-sentinel-data-lake-unify-signals-cut-costs-and-power-agentic-ai/">Microsoft Sentinel data lake: Unify signals, cut costs, and power agentic AI</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog">Microsoft Security Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p class="wp-block-paragraph">You can’t protect what you can’t see. Security operations teams have long been faced with the challenge of managing massive, fast-growing datasets, and the cost of scaling traditional data management tools to handle these data volumes has become unsustainable. We’re evolving our industry-leading Security Incidents and Event Management solution (SIEM), <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/security/business/siem-and-xdr/microsoft-sentinel/">Microsoft Sentinel</a>, to include a modern, cost-effective data lake. By unifying all your security data, <strong>Microsoft Sentinel data lake, now in public preview</strong>, accelerates agentic AI adoption and drives unparalleled visibility, empowering teams to detect and respond faster. With Sentinel data lake, you’re no longer forced to choose between retaining critical data and staying within budget.</p>



<div class="wp-block-buttons is-content-justification-center is-layout-flex wp-container-core-buttons-is-layout-1 wp-block-buttons-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-button"><a class="wp-block-button__link wp-element-button" href="https://www.microsoft.com/security/business/siem-and-xdr/microsoft-sentinel/">Learn more about Microsoft Sentinel</a></div>
</div>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"></p>


<div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
			<div class="ms-metrics-youtube-container" data-video-id="MIlQfgiyUz8" id="ms-metrics-youtube-6882923c73a28">
				<div class="ms-metrics-youtube-player"></div>
			</div>
		</div>


<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Microsoft Sentinel started on this journey five years ago with the introduction of the first cloud-native SIEM to simplify data onboarding and bring the power of AI to threat detection.¹ Since then, we’ve integrated Sentinel with Microsoft Defender and enriched it with real-time threat intelligence, guided recommendations, and automated response capabilities. Microsoft Sentinel data lake is the next step in that journey—built to help security leaders break through the limitations of traditional SIEMs by putting security data at the center of the security operations center (SOC), at scale, and without compromise. Now, you can continue your own journey and <a href="https://aka.ms/sentineldatalakedocs" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">onboard Microsoft Sentinel data lake</a>.</p>


<div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
			<div class="ms-metrics-youtube-container" data-video-id="b8Gcmy2ed5U" id="ms-metrics-youtube-6882923c73b0b">
				<div class="ms-metrics-youtube-player"></div>
			</div>
		</div>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="breaking-down-data-silos-for-better-security">Breaking down data silos for better security</h2>



<div class="alignright wp-block-bloginabox-theme-kicker" data-bi-an="Kicker Left">
	<div class="kicker">
		<h2 class="kicker__title">
			WHAT is SIEM?		</h2>
		<p class="kicker__content">
							<a
					href="https://www.microsoft.com/security/business/security-101/what-is-siem"
					class="kicker__link"
					target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"				>
						Learn more							↗</a>
					</p>
	</div>
</div>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">With security log volumes growing fast, teams are forced into making painful tradeoffs: reduce logging by risking blind spots, shorten retention by compromising forensic depth, or absorb unsustainable costs when aiming to manage all their security data within a SIEM. This is the paradox of modern security: the more data you have, the harder it becomes to use it effectively. And without unified, long-term visibility, even the most advanced AI models can’t deliver to their full potential. Siloed data means missed cyberthreats, delayed investigations, and underutilized tools.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Microsoft Sentinel data lake was purpose-built to solve this challenge and provides the foundation for agentic defense. It brings together all your security data, from Microsoft and third-party sources, into a single, cost-effective data lake, with more than 350 native connectors. With data retention priced at less than 15% of traditional analytics logs, it enables seamless enrichment with threat intelligence and AI-powered detection across your entire environment. This isn’t just a new product, it’s a new architecture for security operations—one that empowers security teams to hunt cyberthreats across months or years, reconstruct incidents with precision, and unlock the full value of AI.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote has-quote-default-font-size is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><em>Microsoft’s vision for Sentinel data lake reflects what matters most in cybersecurity: clarity, scale, and real-world impact. With more than 1,200 Sentinel deployments worldwide, BlueVoyant has seen the need firsthand. Large scale data challenges are now the norm. Sentinel data lake marks a natural evolution of the SIEM and SOAR model, one that critically supports modern analytics, data science, and flexible ingestion strategy. It is a critical step forward for customers looking to modernize their security operations.</em></p>
<cite>—Milan Patel, Chief Revenue Officer at BlueVoyant</cite></blockquote>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">To further help defenders get the most out of their data, we’re democratizing threat intelligence by converging&nbsp;<a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/business/siem-and-xdr/microsoft-defender-threat-intelligence?msockid=3793858bb492626d36189079b50d634e" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Microsoft Defender Threat Intelligence</a> (MDTI) capabilities into Defender XDR and Sentinel at no additional cost; this means that security teams will no longer need to buy a separate SKU to access these powerful features. MDTI value will be merged in Sentinel and Defender XDR over time, starting in October 2025 when all Microsoft first-party threat reports, including intel profiles and indicators of compromise (IoCs), will be available in Defender XDR. Additionally, IoCs will be incorporated into Sentinel case management so customers can collaborate and share threat intelligence across teams within their organization. The remaining features will become available over time. </p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">With this change, security teams can easily tap into a powerful repository of frontline threat intelligence, sourced from&nbsp;84 trillion daily signals and backed by the expertise of more than 10,000 Microsoft security specialists.&nbsp;<a href="http://aka.ms/mdti-convergence" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Read more</a> about how this added value in Sentinel and Defender will greatly enhance capabilities with real-time, high-quality threat data.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="empowering-security-teams-to-do-more"><strong>Empowering security teams to do more</strong></h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">The promise of AI in cybersecurity has always been bold: faster detection, smarter response, and the ability to outpace even the most sophisticated cyberattackers. But most security teams are held back by fragmented data and incomplete context. Centralizing your data in a threat intel-enriched data lake eliminates silos and ensures AI models like Security Copilot have the full context they need to detect subtle cyberattack patterns, correlate signals across time and space, and surface high-fidelity alerts. This creates the foundation for the future of agentic defense where AI doesn’t just assist, it acts. This shift now empowers security teams to:</p>



<div class="alignright wp-block-bloginabox-theme-kicker" data-bi-an="Kicker Left">
	<div class="kicker">
		<h2 class="kicker__title">
			What are indicators of compromise?		</h2>
		<p class="kicker__content">
							<a
					href="https://www.microsoft.com/security/business/security-101/what-are-indicators-of-compromise-ioc"
					class="kicker__link"
					target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"				>
						Learn more							↗</a>
					</p>
	</div>
</div>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item">Uncover cyberattacker behavior going back years without worrying as much about storage limits</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Address pre-breach and post-breach use cases by correlating asset, activity, and TI data</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Utilize real-time threat intel to triage faster and retroactively hunt over historical data</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Trigger detections automatically based on the latest IoCs and tactics, techniques, and procedures (TTPs)</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Use Kusto Query Language (KQL) and Apache Spark to query across extended time horizons and detect subtle cyberattack patterns</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Support regulatory and compliance needs with scalable, cost-efficient data retention</li>
</ul>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">These are the jobs that matter most in modern security operations and now they’re easier, faster, and more cost-effective to execute.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote has-quote-default-font-size is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><em><em>For cyber teams, the massive proliferation of data can misdirect focus or delay responses to genuine [cyber]threats. Microsoft Sentinel data lake can be a valuable tool for data centralization and visibility and for historical analysis across large volumes of datasets. Together with Microsoft, Accenture can help our clients leverage the data lake to extend the power of Microsoft Sentinel to supercharge attack detection and proactive remediation.</em></em><a id="_msocom_1"></a></p>
<cite><em>—</em>Rex Thexton, Chief Technology Officer, Accenture Security</cite></blockquote>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="simplifying-operations-while-being-ai-ready">Simplifying operations while being AI-ready</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Microsoft Sentinel data lake simplifies data management with a flexible, centralized experience in the <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/security/business/solutions/ai-powered-unified-secops-platform" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Microsoft Defender</a> portal—bringing your security data together alongside the tools your defenders use to prevent, detect, and respond to cyberthreats every day. Analysts can move seamlessly between the analytics and data lake tiers, enabling real-time response and deep investigation from a single interface. While doing that all your data stored in the analytics tier is automatically available in the data lake tier, and because it’s built on open formats, organizations can tailor analytics workflows, build custom machine learning (ML) models, and leverage familiar tools, over a single copy of their security data, to extend the value of the data lake to meet their unique needs. Whether you&#8217;re consolidating tools, scaling your SOC, or preparing for AI-powered defense, Sentinel data lake adapts to your security strategy and journey.</p>


<figure data-wp-context="{&quot;imageId&quot;:&quot;6882923c7789a&quot;}" data-wp-interactive="core/image" class="wp-block-image size-large wp-lightbox-container"><img decoding="async" data-wp-class--hide="state.isContentHidden" data-wp-class--show="state.isContentVisible" data-wp-init="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox" data-wp-on-async--load="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async-window--resize="callbacks.setButtonStyles" src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/MS_Security_Sentinel_Datalake_Infographic_DataLake_Light_Alt_PNG-4-1024x576.webp" alt="A view of the new data lake architecture and how it interacts with the Sentinel SIEM. " class="wp-image-141343 webp-format" srcset="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/MS_Security_Sentinel_Datalake_Infographic_DataLake_Light_Alt_PNG-4-1024x576.webp 1024w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/MS_Security_Sentinel_Datalake_Infographic_DataLake_Light_Alt_PNG-4-300x169.webp 300w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/MS_Security_Sentinel_Datalake_Infographic_DataLake_Light_Alt_PNG-4-768x432.webp 768w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/MS_Security_Sentinel_Datalake_Infographic_DataLake_Light_Alt_PNG-4-1536x864.webp 1536w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/MS_Security_Sentinel_Datalake_Infographic_DataLake_Light_Alt_PNG-4-809x455.webp 809w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/MS_Security_Sentinel_Datalake_Infographic_DataLake_Light_Alt_PNG-4.webp 1921w" data-orig-src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/MS_Security_Sentinel_Datalake_Infographic_DataLake_Light_Alt_PNG-4-1024x576.webp"><button
			class="lightbox-trigger"
			type="button"
			aria-haspopup="dialog"
			aria-label="Enlarge image: A view of the new data lake architecture and how it interacts with the Sentinel SIEM. "
			data-wp-init="callbacks.initTriggerButton"
			data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox"
			data-wp-style--right="state.imageButtonRight"
			data-wp-style--top="state.imageButtonTop"
		>
			<svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="12" height="12" fill="none" viewBox="0 0 12 12">
				<path fill="#fff" d="M2 0a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v2h1.5V2a.5.5 0 0 1 .5-.5h2V0H2Zm2 10.5H2a.5.5 0 0 1-.5-.5V8H0v2a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h2v-1.5ZM8 12v-1.5h2a.5.5 0 0 0 .5-.5V8H12v2a2 2 0 0 1-2 2H8Zm2-12a2 2 0 0 1 2 2v2h-1.5V2a.5.5 0 0 0-.5-.5H8V0h2Z" />
			</svg>
		</button></figure>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><a id="_msocom_2"></a></p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Sentinel data lake enables SOC teams into the next era of security operations. Being able to ensure coverage of your security estate—across all security data sources and vast time horizons—enables security teams to proactively detect latent cyberattacks, detect emerging cyberthreats with AI-powered models, reconstruct cyberattack timelines in forensic detail, and retroactively uncover indicators of compromise that might otherwise go unnoticed.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote has-quote-default-font-size is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><em>The [cyber]attack surface is expanding with every application and AI application deployed across hybrid cloud environments, and AI-powered attacks are evolving just as fast. What many organizations still lack isn’t just better tools—it’s ​real-time visibility of their IT estate, their configurations and business context. To understand their full exposure, organizations need the right asset intelligence and a shared&nbsp;industry effort.&nbsp;The new Microsoft Sentinel data lake represents a valuable step in that direction; IBM is committed to working across the ecosystem to help solve that challenge.</em></p>
<cite> —Srini Tummalapenta, IBM Distinguished Engineer, Chief Technology Officer for IBM Consulting Cybersecurity Services</cite></blockquote>



<div class="alignright wp-block-bloginabox-theme-kicker" data-bi-an="Kicker Left">
	<div class="kicker">
		<h2 class="kicker__title">
			What is extended detection and response?		</h2>
		<p class="kicker__content">
							<a
					href="https://www.microsoft.com/security/business/security-101/what-is-xdr"
					class="kicker__link"
					target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"				>
						Learn more							↗</a>
					</p>
	</div>
</div>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">This launch marks more than a product evolution enabling security operations teams to respond faster and with maximum visibility. Microsoft Sentinel is continuing to push the boundaries with a scalable architecture that combines SIEM, extended detection and response (XDR), and threat intelligence into a single, integrated experience. Sentinel data lake is the foundation of this evolution, enabling security teams to reason over more data, more intelligently, and more affordably than ever before.</p>



<div class="is-style-inline wp-block-bloginabox-theme-promotional">
	
<div class="promotional promotional--has-media promotional--media-right">
	<div class="promotional__wrapper">
		<div class="promotional__content-wrapper">
			<div class="promotional__content">
				

<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="microsoft-security-innovation">Microsoft Security Innovation</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Join us to explore the next wave of AI-first end-to-end security innovation at the upcoming digital event on September 30, 2025. <br><br><a data-bi-an="Global CTA" data-bi-ct="cta link" data-bi-id="cta-block" href="https://aka.ms/SecurityInnovationReg" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Sign up to be notified when registration opens</a></p>

			</div>
		</div>
					<div class="promotional__media-wrapper">
				<div class="promotional__media">
											<img decoding="async" width="8192" height="5464" src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/CLO25-SCI-Lifestyle-054.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="Close up of hands typing on keyboard of Surface tablet." loading="lazy" srcset="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/CLO25-SCI-Lifestyle-054.jpg 8192w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/CLO25-SCI-Lifestyle-054-300x200.jpg 300w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/CLO25-SCI-Lifestyle-054-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/CLO25-SCI-Lifestyle-054-768x512.jpg 768w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/CLO25-SCI-Lifestyle-054-1536x1025.jpg 1536w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 8192px) 100vw, 8192px" />									</div>
			</div>
			</div>
</div>
</div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="get-started-today">Get started today</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Microsoft Sentinel data lake is now in preview. Join us as we redefine what’s possible in security operations:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item"><a href="https://aka.ms/sentineldatalakedocs">Onboard Sentinel data lake</a></li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Learn more about the latest news in <a href="http://aka.ms/datalaketechblog">our Tech Community blog</a></li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Explore <a href="https://aka.ms/sentinel/pricingblog">our pricing</a></li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Learn more about our <a href="http://aka.ms/mdti-convergence">MDTI news</a></li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Sign up for<a href="https://aka.ms/SecurityInnovationReg"> next wave of innovation</a></li>
</ul>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">To learn more about Microsoft Security solutions, visit our&nbsp;<a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/business" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">website</a>.&nbsp;Bookmark the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.microsoft.com/security/blog/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Security blog</a>&nbsp;to keep up with our expert coverage on security matters. Also, follow us on LinkedIn (<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/showcase/microsoft-security/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Microsoft Security</a>) and X (<a href="https://twitter.com/@MSFTSecurity" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">@MSFTSecurity</a>)&nbsp;for the latest news and updates on cybersecurity.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">¹<a href="https://blogs.microsoft.com/blog/2019/02/28/announcing-new-cloud-based-technology-to-empower-cyber-defenders/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Announcing new cloud-based technology to empower cyber defenders</a>, Official Microsoft Blog. Ann Johnson. Feb 28, 2019.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/2025/07/22/microsoft-sentinel-data-lake-unify-signals-cut-costs-and-power-agentic-ai/">Microsoft Sentinel data lake: Unify signals, cut costs, and power agentic AI</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog">Microsoft Security Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Microsoft at Black Hat USA 2025: A unified approach to modern cyber defense</title>
		<link>https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/blog/microsoft-security-blog/%E2%80%8B%E2%80%8Bmicrosoft-at-black-hat-usa-2025-a-unified-approach-to-modern-cyber-defense%E2%80%8B%E2%80%8B/4434292</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Elliot Volkman]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/?p=141276</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Microsoft will spotlight its AI-first, end-to-end security platform at Black Hat USA 2025. Read our blog post for details on how to connect with us there and what to expect from our participation.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/blog/microsoft-security-blog/%E2%80%8B%E2%80%8Bmicrosoft-at-black-hat-usa-2025-a-unified-approach-to-modern-cyber-defense%E2%80%8B%E2%80%8B/4434292">Microsoft at Black Hat USA 2025: A unified approach to modern cyber defense</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog">Microsoft Security Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Microsoft will be at Black Hat USA 2025, August 5–7 in Las Vegas, and we’re bringing you a unified, practitioner-driven experience built around real-world insights, threat intelligence, incident response, and hands-on AI expertise.<br>We believe security teams are strongest when intelligence, tools, and deep expertise come together. At Microsoft, we’ve eliminated internal silos between threat intelligence, red teaming, incident response, and product engineering. That closed-loop system lets us move faster, translating threat signals into global protection every day.<br>This integration isn’t theoretical. It means when researchers detect a threat through our global network, that information flows directly to the red team stress-testing our defenses, the incident responders investigating real intrusions, and the engineering teams building new mitigations; all at once. It&#8217;s a system designed to learn, adapt, and protect at scale. At Black Hat, we’re opening that loop so you can see how it works and inviting you to see how it can help you defend at AI speed. Want to meet the people behind our operations? Request an invite to our Black Hat VIP mixer.<br>Start your Black Hat journey early with the Microsoft Threat Intelligence Podcast<br>Before Black Hat kicks off, hear from Black Hat NOC lead Grifter and Lintile in our latest episode of the Microsoft Threat Intelligence Podcast. They explore what it takes to secure one of the world’s most high-profile cybersecurity conferences, what the Black Hat Network Operations Center (NOC) sees in real time, and how defenders can apply those lessons to their own environments. Whether you&#8217;re attending in person or following along remotely, this episode offers a rare look into threat activity and security insights from inside the NOC.<br>Meet us at Booth 2246: Conversations, not presentations</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Skip the crowded theater sessions and pull up a chair. Throughout the day, we’re hosting informal conversations at our mobile podcast studio and then shifting to expert meetups where your questions will be answered. At booth 2246, you’ll hear directly from Microsoft security experts on what they’re seeing, and how you can apply it. Topics include:</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">• Addressing the ransomware threat landscape<br>• Defending against BEC attacks<br>• Shifts in social engineering and phishing<br>• Securing non-human identities (agents)<br>• And a few surprises</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">We’ll also be inviting our friends from the Microsoft Threat Intelligence Podcast, Microsoft BlueHat podcast (MSRC), GitHub, and a few special guests.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Each session is a chance to hear what our teams are seeing in the wild, how we’re responding, and how you can apply those insights in your own environment. Whether it&#8217;s a live threat briefing, a deep dive into red teaming, or a behind-the-scenes look at real incident response, these are unscripted, interactive discussions designed for defenders and researchers.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Demos of Microsoft Defender, Microsoft Entra, Microsoft Purview, and Microsoft Security Copilot will run throughout the week. Stop by to talk shop, ask questions, or just get a clearer view of why our AI-first, end-to-end platform is designed to help you move faster, respond with precision, and adapt to new threats with confidence.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Connect with the experts at our VIP Mixer</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">You’re invited to connect with the people behind the defense at our VIP Mixer on Wednesday, Aug. 6. Join Microsoft Security for an evening of conversations, insights, and connections with our threat intelligence, incident response, and Security Copilot teams, alongside your peers from across the security community.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Whether you&#8217;re exploring how to put AI agents to work, navigating advanced threats, or evolving your detection and response strategy, this is your chance to meet the experts and teams helping defenders stay ahead.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Security is a team sport, and we would like to thank Armor, Cyberproof, Forescout, Ontinue and Security Risk Advisors members of the Microsoft Intelligent Security Association (MISA) for sponsoring this event.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Drinks and appetizers will be provided. Request to attend today!</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Session Spotlight: Gain practical strategies for unmasking cyber threats</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Thursday, August 7 | 12:15–12:40 PM<br>In a threat landscape shaped by AI and threat actors, cybersecurity teams need more than tools; they need the right mindset, collaboration models, and playbooks to stay ahead. During our main stage session, we will bring together frontline experts from Microsoft Security—Sherrod DeGrippo, Director, Threat Intelligence Strategy, Aarti Borkar, Corporate Vice President, Customer Success and Incident Response, Andrew Rapp, Leader, Incident Response and Simeon Kakpovi, —to share how they approach high-impact intrusions and what defenders everywhere can take away from it.<br>This session will offer practical strategies grounded in real-world operations, including:<br>• How to build tighter alignment across threat intel, IR, and detection teams<br>• Approaches to reduce friction and accelerate signal-to-action response time<br>• Lessons from tracking threat actors focused on social engineering and ransomware<br>• Ways to adapt red teaming and detection in a rapidly evolving AI landscape<br>Whether you&#8217;re refining your team’s structure or looking for sharper ways to think about advanced threats, this conversation will deliver actionable insight you can bring back to your own environment.<br>Inside Look: How Microsoft Red Teams Stay in Sync<br>Wednesday, August 6 | 11:25–11:45 AM<br>What happens when red teams operate not in isolation, but as a connected part of a broader defense ecosystem?<br>Microsoft security experts Ram Shankar Siva Kumar (founder of the AI Red Team) and Craig Nelson (Microsoft Red Team) will explore how traditional and AI red teams work side by side to proactively test Microsoft’s products, platforms, and AI systems.<br>You’ll hear how these teams:<br>• Identify systemic risks across cloud and enterprise services<br>• Probe generative AI systems for jailbreaks and indirect misuse<br>• Collaborate with MSRC and threat researchers to close the loop from discovery to defense<br>• Embed red teaming into engineering cycles, not just as a check, but as a design influence<br>Whether you’re red-teaming your own products or rethinking how to operationalize adversarial testing, this session will offer lessons in collaboration, tooling, and mindset from two of the most advanced offensive security teams in the industry.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Exchange ideas with other MISA members<br>The Microsoft booth will include a featured partner demo station where 7 partners from the Microsoft Intelligent Security Association (MISA) will showcase how their solutions together with Microsoft Security technology help defend our mutual customers from cybersecurity threats.<br>Connect with us at the Microsoft booth to find out more.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Connect with us at Black Hat US<br>Cybersecurity is a team sport and defending against threats takes a cohesive approach that brings multiple disciplines and experts across specialties together. We’re committed to eliminating internal silos to focus on threat hunting that supports a comprehensive defense.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">You’ll hear more of this approach and how it can benefit your organization at Black Hat US.<br>• Check out Microsoft Security executives at the AI Summit at Black Hat (separate pass required)<br>• Request to attend our VIP Mixer to meet the experts behind Microsoft threat intelligence, incident response, and the Microsoft Security Response Center.<br>• Discover how our end-to-end platform can help you strengthen resilience and elevate your security posture.<br>• Get an exclusive $200 briefings and $100 business hall pass discount to share with your customers and prospects.<br>• Sign up for a one-on-one meeting with Microsoft Security experts.<br>• Listen to our Threat Intelligence Podcast.<br>Visit us in Booth #2246 for a live demo and learn how our AI-powered cybersecurity can protect your organization.<br>Hope to see you at Black Hat!</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/blog/microsoft-security-blog/%E2%80%8B%E2%80%8Bmicrosoft-at-black-hat-usa-2025-a-unified-approach-to-modern-cyber-defense%E2%80%8B%E2%80%8B/4434292">Microsoft at Black Hat USA 2025: A unified approach to modern cyber defense</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog">Microsoft Security Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Transparency on Microsoft Defender for Office 365 email security effectiveness</title>
		<link>https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/2025/07/17/transparency-on-microsoft-defender-for-office-365-email-security-effectiveness/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ramya Chitrakar and Scott Woodgate]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/?p=140177</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Microsoft believes in transparently sharing performance data from Microsoft Defender for Office 365, and other ecosystem providers, to help customers evaluate email security solutions and make decisions to layer for defense in depth. </p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/2025/07/17/transparency-on-microsoft-defender-for-office-365-email-security-effectiveness/">Transparency on Microsoft Defender for Office 365 email security effectiveness</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog">Microsoft Security Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p class="wp-block-paragraph">In today’s world, cyberattackers are relentless. They are often well-resourced, highly sophisticated, and constantly innovating, which means the effectiveness of cybersecurity solutions must be continuously evaluated, not assumed. Yet, despite the critical role email security plays in protecting organizations, there is limited transparency and standardization in how email security effectiveness is measured and communicated. This makes it challenging for chief information security officers (CISOs) and security architects to make decisions based on data. </p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">At Microsoft, we believe that transparency is foundational to trust. As both an email platform and a security provider, we want to work together with our ecosystem and do more to empower customers to understand email security effectiveness. Today, we’re announcing two initiatives to support that objective.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">First, to provide <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/security/business/siem-and-xdr/microsoft-defender-office-365">Microsoft Defender for Office 365</a> customers with richer data on its efficacy, we are releasing a new customer-facing dashboard that will provide visibility on our effectiveness across a range of threat vectors.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Second, we are releasing two comparative benchmarking reports designed to assist customers in evaluating the benefits of integrating multiple email security solutions. The first describes the protection value added by Integrated Cloud Email Security (ICES) vendors, which detect and remediate threats after Microsoft Defender for Office 365. The second describes the value of Secure Email Gateways (SEGs), which filter emails before they reach Microsoft Defender for Office 365. These reports are based on real-world threat data rather than synthetic tests to provide an objective basis for comparison at scale.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Security is a team sport, and we are grateful to our entire ecosystem for working together on protecting our customers. We encourage customers to see how the solutions deployed in their tenants are collectively performing for their needs.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="introducing-the-defender-for-office-365-overview-dashboard">Introducing the Defender for Office 365 overview dashboard</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">The new customer overview dashboard allows security teams to track efficacy across cyberthreats blocked pre-delivery, threats mitigated post-delivery, and even “missed” threats. It includes details on how Microsoft Defender for Office 365 capabilities like Safe link, Safe attachments, and Zero-hour Auto Purge contribute to threat protection across an organization. Our goal is simple: to help you confidently answer the question “How are my organization&#8217;s users being protected from malicious content and cyberattacks when using email and other collaboration surfaces like Microsoft Teams?” </p>


<figure data-wp-context="{&quot;imageId&quot;:&quot;6882923c8e142&quot;}" data-wp-interactive="core/image" class="wp-block-image size-full wp-lightbox-container"><img decoding="async" data-wp-class--hide="state.isContentHidden" data-wp-class--show="state.isContentVisible" data-wp-init="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox" data-wp-on-async--load="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async-window--resize="callbacks.setButtonStyles" src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture1-3.webp" alt="A screenshot of the new Defender for Office 365 overview dashboard." class="wp-image-141231 webp-format" srcset="" data-orig-src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture1-3.webp"><button
			class="lightbox-trigger"
			type="button"
			aria-haspopup="dialog"
			aria-label="Enlarge image: A screenshot of the new Defender for Office 365 overview dashboard."
			data-wp-init="callbacks.initTriggerButton"
			data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox"
			data-wp-style--right="state.imageButtonRight"
			data-wp-style--top="state.imageButtonTop"
		>
			<svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="12" height="12" fill="none" viewBox="0 0 12 12">
				<path fill="#fff" d="M2 0a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v2h1.5V2a.5.5 0 0 1 .5-.5h2V0H2Zm2 10.5H2a.5.5 0 0 1-.5-.5V8H0v2a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h2v-1.5ZM8 12v-1.5h2a.5.5 0 0 0 .5-.5V8H12v2a2 2 0 0 1-2 2H8Zm2-12a2 2 0 0 1 2 2v2h-1.5V2a.5.5 0 0 0-.5-.5H8V0h2Z" />
			</svg>
		</button></figure>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><em>Figure 1. Transparent Reporting Overview Dashboard</em>.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="benchmarking">Benchmarking</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Transparency on effectiveness of Microsoft products alone isn’t enough. We know customers need data to evaluate effectiveness across the entire ecosystem, and our benchmarking research is intended to help you plan your cybersecurity solutions end to end.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Unlike traditional benchmarks that rely on synthetic tests or artificial environments, our reports use real email threats observed in the Microsoft ecosystem. We specifically compared environments protected solely by Microsoft Defender for Office 365 with those where an SEG was deployed in front of Defender, and with those where additional protection was provided by ICES vendors layered after Defender for Office 365. Throughout this process, we adhered to our strict security and privacy principles; all data presented in this report is aggregated and anonymized similar to data published in the Microsoft Digital Defense Report.</p>


<figure data-wp-context="{&quot;imageId&quot;:&quot;6882923c910f9&quot;}" data-wp-interactive="core/image" class="wp-block-image size-large wp-lightbox-container"><img decoding="async" data-wp-class--hide="state.isContentHidden" data-wp-class--show="state.isContentVisible" data-wp-init="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox" data-wp-on-async--load="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async-window--resize="callbacks.setButtonStyles" src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/photo-1024x553.webp" alt="A screenshot of a computer screen." class="wp-image-141247 webp-format" srcset="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/photo-1024x553.webp 1024w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/photo-300x162.webp 300w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/photo-768x415.webp 768w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/photo-1536x830.webp 1536w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/photo.webp 1801w" data-orig-src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/photo-1024x553.webp"><button
			class="lightbox-trigger"
			type="button"
			aria-haspopup="dialog"
			aria-label="Enlarge image: A screenshot of a computer screen."
			data-wp-init="callbacks.initTriggerButton"
			data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox"
			data-wp-style--right="state.imageButtonRight"
			data-wp-style--top="state.imageButtonTop"
		>
			<svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="12" height="12" fill="none" viewBox="0 0 12 12">
				<path fill="#fff" d="M2 0a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v2h1.5V2a.5.5 0 0 1 .5-.5h2V0H2Zm2 10.5H2a.5.5 0 0 1-.5-.5V8H0v2a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h2v-1.5ZM8 12v-1.5h2a.5.5 0 0 0 .5-.5V8H12v2a2 2 0 0 1-2 2H8Zm2-12a2 2 0 0 1 2 2v2h-1.5V2a.5.5 0 0 0-.5-.5H8V0h2Z" />
			</svg>
		</button></figure>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><em>Figure 2. Secure Email Gateway and Integrated Cloud Email Security vendors landscape</em>.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="benchmarking-seg-vendors">Benchmarking SEG vendors</h3>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">SEGs continue to play an important role in many organizations’ security architectures, offering additional layers of protection. Microsoft benchmarked seven SEG vendors and Microsoft Defender for Office 365.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading" id="methodology"><strong>Methodology</strong></h4>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Microsoft analyzed aggregated threat signals from environments using specific SEGs with Defender for Office 365, then normalized the results per 1,000 protected users to measure missed threats.&nbsp;</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">For SEG vendors, a threat was considered “missed” if it was not detected pre-delivery, or if it was not removed shortly after delivery (post-delivery). However, for Microsoft Defender for Office 365, we applied a stricter standard; even if the threat was removed post-delivery, it was considered as missed. &nbsp;</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading" id="results"><strong>Results</strong></h4>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">This analysis showed that, when baselined against Defender for Office, Defender for Office missed the least threats.</p>


<figure data-wp-context="{&quot;imageId&quot;:&quot;6882923c9426c&quot;}" data-wp-interactive="core/image" class="wp-block-image size-large wp-lightbox-container"><img decoding="async" data-wp-class--hide="state.isContentHidden" data-wp-class--show="state.isContentVisible" data-wp-init="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox" data-wp-on-async--load="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async-window--resize="callbacks.setButtonStyles" src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture2-1-1024x578.webp" alt="A chart that shows how many email threats are missed by other secure email gateway vendors. " class="wp-image-141234 webp-format" srcset="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture2-1-1024x578.webp 1024w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture2-1-300x169.webp 300w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture2-1-768x434.webp 768w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture2-1-1536x867.webp 1536w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture2-1.webp 1869w" data-orig-src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture2-1-1024x578.webp"><button
			class="lightbox-trigger"
			type="button"
			aria-haspopup="dialog"
			aria-label="Enlarge image: A chart that shows how many email threats are missed by other secure email gateway vendors. "
			data-wp-init="callbacks.initTriggerButton"
			data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox"
			data-wp-style--right="state.imageButtonRight"
			data-wp-style--top="state.imageButtonTop"
		>
			<svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="12" height="12" fill="none" viewBox="0 0 12 12">
				<path fill="#fff" d="M2 0a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v2h1.5V2a.5.5 0 0 1 .5-.5h2V0H2Zm2 10.5H2a.5.5 0 0 1-.5-.5V8H0v2a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h2v-1.5ZM8 12v-1.5h2a.5.5 0 0 0 .5-.5V8H12v2a2 2 0 0 1-2 2H8Zm2-12a2 2 0 0 1 2 2v2h-1.5V2a.5.5 0 0 0-.5-.5H8V0h2Z" />
			</svg>
		</button></figure>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><em>Figure 3. Secure Email Gateway (SEG) Vendor Benchmark Data</em>.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="ices-vendors">ICES vendors</h3>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">As organizations adopt layered security strategies, ICES products execute after Microsoft Defender for Office 365 and act as a secondary filter. These solutions offer additional detection layers focusing on specific threat types or user behavior patterns.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading" id="methodology-1"><strong>Methodology</strong></h4>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">ICES vendors use the <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/graph/use-the-api" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Microsoft Graph API</a> to move emails to folders such as junk, promotional, or deleted items. &nbsp;&nbsp;Messages can be moved from any delivery location, like the Inbox or even the Junk folder. In this data study, a message moved by an ICES vendor is counted as a catch. Messages marked as spam or malicious by Microsoft Defender for Office 365 <em>before</em> the ICES vendor moved them, are counted as duplicate catch. Generally, messages classified as spam by Microsoft Defender for Office 365 are delivered to the Junk folder and those classified as malicious go to Quarantine. However, some customer configurations can override message delivery. The ICES vendor catch is normalized by Microsoft Defender for Office 365’s overall catch to make it simple to see the value added by ICES vendor.</p>


<figure data-wp-context="{&quot;imageId&quot;:&quot;6882923c971fd&quot;}" data-wp-interactive="core/image" class="wp-block-image size-full wp-lightbox-container"><img decoding="async" data-wp-class--hide="state.isContentHidden" data-wp-class--show="state.isContentVisible" data-wp-init="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox" data-wp-on-async--load="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async-window--resize="callbacks.setButtonStyles" src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture3-1.webp" alt="A chart that summarizes the incremental detection contributions from ICES vendors across several categories." class="wp-image-141237 webp-format" srcset="" data-orig-src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture3-1.webp"><button
			class="lightbox-trigger"
			type="button"
			aria-haspopup="dialog"
			aria-label="Enlarge image: A chart that summarizes the incremental detection contributions from ICES vendors across several categories."
			data-wp-init="callbacks.initTriggerButton"
			data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox"
			data-wp-style--right="state.imageButtonRight"
			data-wp-style--top="state.imageButtonTop"
		>
			<svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="12" height="12" fill="none" viewBox="0 0 12 12">
				<path fill="#fff" d="M2 0a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v2h1.5V2a.5.5 0 0 1 .5-.5h2V0H2Zm2 10.5H2a.5.5 0 0 1-.5-.5V8H0v2a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h2v-1.5ZM8 12v-1.5h2a.5.5 0 0 0 .5-.5V8H12v2a2 2 0 0 1-2 2H8Zm2-12a2 2 0 0 1 2 2v2h-1.5V2a.5.5 0 0 0-.5-.5H8V0h2Z" />
			</svg>
		</button></figure>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><em>Figure 4. Integrated Cloud Email Security Vendor Benchmark Data</em>.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Definitions for the categories used are:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item"><strong>Marketing and bulk</strong>—Promotional offers or newsletters from known senders (for example, a coupon from a food delivery app) that are not malicious but may affect productivity.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item"><strong>Spam</strong>—Nuisance emails from unsolicited or disreputable senders that are not malicious but may affect productivity.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item"><strong>Malicious</strong>—Messages containing harmful content such as phishing links, malware, or other security threats.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item"><strong>Non-malicious</strong>—Benign messages that could be false positives or may have been moved due to customer preferences.</li>
</ul>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Our analysis shows that combining ICES products with Defender for Office 365 yields the greatest impact in enhancing detection of promotional or bulk email, with an average improvement of 20%. These enhancements can help reduce inbox clutter to improve user experience, particularly in environments where marketing noise is a concern, and offer valuable insight for us as we consider continued investment in enabling roadmap capabilities that benefit our customers. For malicious messages and spam, across all vendors analyzed, the average improvement was 0.30% for malicious catch and 0.51% for spam catch. Look for details on each vendor on the <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/business/siem-and-xdr/microsoft-defender-office-365/performance-benchmarking">benchmarking website</a>.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="empowering-security-through-transparency-and-data">Empowering security through transparency and data</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">In keeping with our commitment to transparency and data-driven rigor, we reached out to SE Labs, recognized experts in email security testing, to independently review our benchmarking methodology, ensuring we hold ourselves to the highest quality standards.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote has-quote-default-font-size is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p class="has-body-large-font-size wp-block-paragraph">“Businesses need to choose the best security that they can afford. Showing the additional benefit vendors provide using real threats, as Microsoft has done here, can help with this important decision.</p>



<p class="has-body-large-font-size wp-block-paragraph">While traditional comparative tests with synthetic threats allow for testing that targets certain features in a product, using specific, advanced, or novel attack techniques, real-world data exposes how products perform against the full spectrum of threats encountered day to day.</p>



<p class="has-body-large-font-size wp-block-paragraph">Both types of testing provide valuable insights that together give a more complete picture of security effectiveness. We hope Microsoft’s data inspires additional comparative testing for better customer decision-making.</p>



<p class="has-body-large-font-size wp-block-paragraph">—Simon Edwards, Founder and Chief Executive Officer, SE Labs</p>
</blockquote>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">In the face of increasingly complex email threats where cybersecurity decisions carry profound consequences, clarity and transparency are indispensable. To support data-driven decisions for our customers, we plan to provide <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/business/siem-and-xdr/microsoft-defender-office-365/performance-benchmarking">quarterly updates for these benchmarks</a> and we will continue to take feedback and refine our approach working together with our ecosystem.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Microsoft remains steadfast in its commitment not only to securing organizations but also to providing reliable tools and actionable transparent data to help you evaluate efficacy and keep your organization safe.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="learn-more">Learn more</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Learn more about <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/business/siem-and-xdr/microsoft-defender-office-365?msockid=3793858bb492626d36189079b50d634e">Microsoft Defender for Office 365</a></p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">To learn more about Microsoft Security solutions, visit our&nbsp;<a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/business" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">website.</a>&nbsp;Bookmark the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.microsoft.com/security/blog/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Security blog</a>&nbsp;to keep up with our expert coverage on security matters. Also, follow us on LinkedIn (<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/showcase/microsoft-security/">Microsoft Security</a>) and X (<a href="https://twitter.com/@MSFTSecurity" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">@MSFTSecurity</a>)&nbsp;for the latest news and updates on cybersecurity.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/2025/07/17/transparency-on-microsoft-defender-for-office-365-email-security-effectiveness/">Transparency on Microsoft Defender for Office 365 email security effectiveness</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog">Microsoft Security Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Microsoft is named a Leader in the 2025 Gartner® Magic Quadrant™ for Endpoint Protection Platforms</title>
		<link>https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/2025/07/16/microsoft-is-named-a-leader-in-the-2025-gartner-magic-quadrant-for-endpoint-protection-platforms/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rob Lefferts]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2025 17:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Gartner Magic Quadrant]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/?p=140727</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>We are honored to be recognized once again as a Leader in the 2025 Gartner® Magic Quadrant™ for Endpoint Protection Platforms—our sixth consecutive time. Microsoft was recognized for its completeness of vision and ability to execute, which we believe underscores the effectiveness of Defender for Endpoint in the face of an ever-shifting threat environment.​</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/2025/07/16/microsoft-is-named-a-leader-in-the-2025-gartner-magic-quadrant-for-endpoint-protection-platforms/">Microsoft is named a Leader in the 2025 Gartner® Magic Quadrant™ for Endpoint Protection Platforms</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog">Microsoft Security Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Since 2022, the number of human-operated ransomware-linked encounters by organizations surged by 2.75x. Yet, Microsoft Defender for Endpoint has outpaced this rise, reducing the number of successful attacks by 3x, proving its power to turn the tide against evolving cyberthreats.<sup>1</sup></p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Defender for Endpoint’s ability to disrupt ransomware at scale stems from our commitment to empowering security analysts against the most sophisticated cyberthreats. <strong>We are honored to be recognized once again as a Leader in the <a href="https://www.gartner.com/reprints/?id=1-2LGE96J2&amp;ct=250715&amp;st=sb" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">2025 Gartner® Magic Quadrant™ for Endpoint Protection Platforms</a>—our sixth consecutive time. </strong>Microsoft was recognized for its completeness of vision and ability to execute, which we believe underscores the effectiveness of Defender for Endpoint in the face of an ever-shifting digital threat environment.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><a href="https://www.microsoft.com/security/business/endpoint-security/microsoft-defender-endpoint">Microsoft Defender for Endpoint</a> is an endpoint security solution that helps organizations secure their digital estate using AI-powered, industry-leading endpoint detection and response across Windows, Linux, macOS, Android, iOS, and Internet of Things (IoT) devices. It is core to Microsoft Defender’s unified security operations platform and built on global threat intelligence informed by more than 84 trillion daily signals and more than 10,000 security experts.<sup>1</sup></p>


<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture1-4-925x1024.webp" alt="A white grid with blue dots." class="wp-image-141266 webp-format" srcset="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture1-4-925x1024.webp 925w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture1-4-271x300.webp 271w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture1-4-768x850.webp 768w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture1-4.webp 1315w" data-orig-src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture1-4-925x1024.webp"></figure>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">We thank our customers and partners for their essential role in advancing Microsoft Security. </p>



<div class="wp-block-buttons is-content-justification-center is-layout-flex wp-container-core-buttons-is-layout-2 wp-block-buttons-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-button has-custom-width wp-block-button__width-75"><a class="wp-block-button__link wp-element-button" href="https://www.microsoft.com/security/business/endpoint-security/microsoft-defender-endpoint">Get started with Microsoft Defender for Endpoint</a></div>
</div>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Over the past year, Microsoft has introduced key advancements to endpoint security that have empowered defenders to stay ahead of evolving cyberthreats, including:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item"><strong>Proactively securing digital environments with exposure management capabilities spanning pre-to-post breach: </strong>Reducing exposure risks like vulnerabilities and misconfigurations is foundational to endpoint security. Defender for Endpoint’s unique visibility into a device estate helps security operations center (SOC) analysts see and harden against their organization’s level of exposure to weaknesses and exploits with an actionable risk score (<a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/security-exposure-management/initiatives" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">endpoint security initiative</a>). In the case of a cyberattack, analysts can further protect the organization and accelerate response with potential <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/security-exposure-management/work-attack-paths-overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">attack paths</a> embedded into the incident. Analysts gain end-to-end visibility into attack paths bad actors may take across devices to reach high-value assets, enabling fast, informed decisions when it matters most.</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item"><strong>Disrupting ransomware attacks even earlier in the cyberattack chain with automatic attack disruption</strong>:<strong> </strong>Unique to Microsoft, <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/defender-xdr/automatic-attack-disruption" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">automatic attack disruption</a> is a built-in self-defense capability that contains in-progress cyberattacks to prevent further lateral movement and damage to an organization. The most pervasive cyberthreat to network-connected devices is ransomware, one of the many scenarios covered by attack disruption. Up to 90% of successful ransomware campaigns leverage unmanaged endpoints, which are typically personal devices that people bring to work.<sup>1</sup> Automatic attack disruption now extends to <a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/blog/microsoftthreatprotectionblog/automatic-attack-disruption-enhanced-containment-for-critical-assets-and-shadow-/4402157" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">unmanaged shadow IT devices and critical assets</a>. Defender for Endpoint can detect and contain malicious IP addresses associated with unmanaged or undiscovered devices. It stops threat actors from exploiting vulnerable entry points, preventing lateral movement before it starts. Attack disruption now also granularly isolates cyberthreats on critical assets such as domain controllers, helping defenders preserve key network functions and ensure operational continuity during an attack.</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item"><strong><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/defender-endpoint/linux-whatsnew" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Enhancing Linux support</a></strong>: Microsoft supports even more&nbsp;Linux distributions, including ARM64 and has reduced resource requirements. These releases reflect the continual progress we’ve made for securing Linux servers on top of our strategic shift over a year ago to eBPF sensor technology that improves system control, minimizes resource demands, and boosts security performance. We’ve also continued delivering cross-platform innovation across <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/microsoft-365/security/defender-endpoint/windows-whatsnew?view=o365-worldwide" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Windows</a>, <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/microsoft-365/security/defender-endpoint/mac-whatsnew?view=o365-worldwide" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">macOS</a>, <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/defender-endpoint/ios-whatsnew" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">iOS</a>, <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/defender-endpoint/android-whatsnew" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Android</a>, and <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/defender-for-iot/organizations/whats-new" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">IoT</a> for comprehensive endpoint security.</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item"><strong>Unifying our agent across XDR workloads</strong>:<strong> </strong><a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/blog/microsoftdefenderatpblog/the-unified-agent-now-combines-protection-across-endpoints-ot-devices-identities/4303805" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">The single agent</a> makes it faster and easier to activate and manage core capabilities across endpoint, operational technology (OT), identity, and data loss prevention workloads so you can quickly unlock the value of AI-powered protection. Organizations simply deploy it once and then enable each solution as needed. Microsoft applies its long-established <a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/blog/microsoftdefenderatpblog/microsoft-defender-for-endpoint%E2%80%99s-safe-deployment-practices/4220342" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">safe deployment practices</a> in delivering the latest protections to help organizations outpace evolving cyberthreats without compromising operational stability. As a part of this process, admins have full control over these software updates.</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item"><strong>Accelerating SOC operations with <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/business/ai-machine-learning/microsoft-security-copilot">Microsoft Security Copilot</a></strong>:<strong> </strong>It is the cybersecurity industry’s first generative AI solution, generally available as of April 2024. Built into the Microsoft Defender portal, it helps SOC analysts investigate, contain, and remediate cyberthreats in minutes. It delivers endpoint-specific capabilities such as recommending tailored guided responses related to devices, analyzing suspicious scripts, and translating natural language questions into ready-to-run Kusto Query Language (KQL) queries. <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/copilot/security/agents-overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Microsoft Security Copilot agents,</a> introduced this year, automate routine tasks by fitting naturally into existing workflows across the security stack. These agents align to Microsoft’s <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/business/zero-trust">Zero Trust principles</a>, learn from feedback, and remain under SOC control.</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item"><strong>Supporting a global SOC:</strong> Security analysts navigate many complexities in their daily operations—language barriers should not be one of them. The Microsoft Defender portal provides experiences in more than 100 languages and dialects. Documentation covers more than 60 languages. This extensive language coverage ensures that analysts can easily navigate, understand, and act with confidence in their native tongue. Wherever the analyst is, Defender likely speaks their language.&nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item"><strong>Extending your SOC team with </strong><a href="https://www.microsoft.com/security/business/services/microsoft-defender-experts-xdr"><strong>Microsoft Defender Experts for XDR</strong></a>: Sophisticated threats span beyond endpoints. We’ve been continually enhancing the capabilities and improving the efficiencies of Microsoft Defender Experts for XDR, our managed XDR service. Defender Experts for XDR offers around-the-clocl, expert-led managed triage, investigation, and response across domains, along with proactive threat hunting—strengthening SOC capabilities around the clock.</li>
</ul>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Market leadership isn’t just about responding to current needs—it&#8217;s about driving the next wave of innovation. Microsoft is investing significantly in helping SOC teams quickly scale their endpoint defenses through foundational enhancements designed to radically simplify deployment and advanced AI-powered autonomous capabilities spanning pre-to-post breach, to name just a couple of highlights for what’s ahead.</p>



<div class="wp-block-buttons is-content-justification-center is-layout-flex wp-container-core-buttons-is-layout-3 wp-block-buttons-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-button has-custom-width wp-block-button__width-100"><a class="wp-block-button__link wp-element-button" href="https://www.microsoft.com/security/business/endpoint-security/microsoft-defender-endpoint-offer">Disrupt ransomware on any platform with Microsoft Defender for Endpoint</a></div>
</div>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Thank you to all our customers and partners. Your partnership drives our mission forward as we work side by side to build a safer, more secure world.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="learn-more">Learn more</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">If you’re not yet taking advantage of Microsoft’s leading endpoint security solution, visit&nbsp;<a href="https://www.microsoft.com/security/business/endpoint-security/microsoft-defender-endpoint-offer">Microsoft Defender for Endpoint</a>&nbsp;and start a free trial today to evaluate our leading endpoint protection platform.&nbsp;</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Are you a regular user of Microsoft Defender for Endpoint? <strong><a href="https://www.gartner.com/peer-insights/login/reviews?TARGET=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.gartner.com%2Fapi%2Fauth%2Fauthorize%3Fresponse_type%3Dcode%26client_id%3Dpi-reviews-web%26state%3DQlDPw4aKOtTOaRP226CEhtJRoKqVfOOOG-Bb-Lbq7mQ%26redirect_uri%3Dhttps%3A%2F%2Fwww.gartner.com%2Freviews%2Fauth%2Fauthorize-completed%3FrefVal%3Dvendor-multi-microsoft-7522095%26regActivity%3Dwrite_a_review%26regChannel%3Dvendor%26code_challenge%3Dl2pgAjNj0mhyGCJYBIBEn2IOaJf7AD9nbZAeQ0dTX-k%26code_challenge_method%3Ds256%26step%3D" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Share your insights</a> on Microsoft Defender for Endpoint and get rewarded with a $25 gift card on Gartner Peer Insights™.</strong></p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">To learn more about Microsoft Security solutions, visit our&nbsp;<a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/business">website.</a>&nbsp;Bookmark the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.microsoft.com/security/blog/">Security blog</a>&nbsp;to keep up with our expert coverage on security matters. Also, follow us on LinkedIn (<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/showcase/microsoft-security/">Microsoft Security</a>) and X (<a href="https://twitter.com/@MSFTSecurity">@MSFTSecurity</a>)&nbsp;for the latest news and updates on cybersecurity.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><sup>1</sup><a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/security-insider/intelligence-reports/microsoft-digital-defense-report-2024?msockid=3bef1be87261641b09e20845732c65d6" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Microsoft Digital Defense Report 2024</a>.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Gartner, Magic Quadrant for Endpoint Protection Platforms, Evgeny Mirolyubov, Deepak Mishra, Franz Hinner. July 14, 2025.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Gartner is a registered trademark and service mark and Magic Quadrant is a registered trademark of Gartner, Inc. and/or its affiliates in the U.S. and internationally and are used herein with permission. All rights reserved.&nbsp;</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">This graphic was published by Gartner, Inc. as part of a larger research document and should be evaluated in the context of the entire document. The Gartner document is available upon request from.<a id="_msocom_1"></a></p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Gartner does not endorse any vendor, product or service depicted in its research publications, and does not advise technology users to select only those vendors with the highest ratings or other designation. Gartner research publications consist of the opinions of Gartner’s research organization and should not be construed as statements of fact. Gartner disclaims all warranties, expressed or implied, with respect to this research, including any warranties of merchantability or fitness for a particular purpose.&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/2025/07/16/microsoft-is-named-a-leader-in-the-2025-gartner-magic-quadrant-for-endpoint-protection-platforms/">Microsoft is named a Leader in the 2025 Gartner® Magic Quadrant™ for Endpoint Protection Platforms</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog">Microsoft Security Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Protecting customers from Octo Tempest attacks across multiple industries</title>
		<link>https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/2025/07/16/protecting-customers-from-octo-tempest-attacks-across-multiple-industries/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Microsoft Defender Security Research Team]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2025 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/?p=141177</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>To help protect and inform customers, Microsoft highlights protection coverage across the Microsoft Defender security ecosystem to protect against threat actors like Octo Tempest.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/2025/07/16/protecting-customers-from-octo-tempest-attacks-across-multiple-industries/">Protecting customers from Octo Tempest attacks across multiple industries</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog">Microsoft Security Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p class="wp-block-paragraph">In recent weeks, Microsoft has observed <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/2023/10/25/octo-tempest-crosses-boundaries-to-facilitate-extortion-encryption-and-destruction/?msockid=0139329c3fb06e3a084e266d3e666fc6" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Octo Tempest</a>, also known as Scattered Spider, impacting the airlines sector, following previous activity impacting retail, food services, hospitality organizations, and insurance between April and July 2025. This aligns with Octo Tempest’s typical patterns of concentrating on one industry for several weeks or months before moving on to new targets. Microsoft Security products continue to update protection coverage as these shifts occur.&nbsp;</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">To help protect and inform customers, this blog highlights the protection coverage across the <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/business/microsoft-defender?msockid=27b7b3bc5be566bc06c9a5a05a7a679d" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Microsoft Defender</a> and Microsoft Sentinel security ecosystem and provides security posture hardening recommendations to protect against threat actors like Octo Tempest.</p>



<div class="wp-block-buttons is-content-justification-center is-layout-flex wp-container-core-buttons-is-layout-4 wp-block-buttons-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-button"><a class="wp-block-button__link wp-element-button" href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/business/microsoft-defender?msockid=27b7b3bc5be566bc06c9a5a05a7a679d">Get ahead of threat actors with integrated security solutions from Microsoft Defender</a></div>
</div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="overview-of-octo-tempest">Overview of Octo Tempest&nbsp;</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Octo Tempest, also known in the industry as Scattered Spider, Muddled Libra, UNC3944, or 0ktapus, is a <a href="https://x.com/FBI/status/1938746767031574565" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">financially motivated cybercriminal group</a> that has been observed impacting organizations using varying methods in their end-to-end attacks. Their approach includes:&nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item">Gaining initial access using social engineering attacks and impersonating a user and contacting service desk support through phone calls, emails, and messages.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Short Message Service (SMS)-based phishing using adversary-in-the-middle (AiTM) domains that mimic legitimate organizations.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Using tools such as ngrok, Chisel, and AADInternals.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Impacting hybrid identity infrastructures and exfiltrating data to support extortion or ransomware operations.&nbsp;&nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Recent activity shows Octo Tempest has deployed DragonForce ransomware with a particular focus on VMWare ESX hypervisor environments. In contrast to previous patterns where Octo Tempest used cloud identity privileges for on-premises access, recent activities have involved impacting both on-premises accounts and infrastructure at the initial stage of an intrusion before transitioning to cloud access.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="octo-tempest-detection-coverage">Octo Tempest detection coverage&nbsp;</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Microsoft Defender has a wide range of detections to detect Octo Tempest related activities and more. These detections span across all areas of the security portfolio including endpoints, identities, software as a service (SaaS) apps, email and collaboration tools, cloud workloads, and more to provide comprehensive protection coverage. Shown below is a list of known Octo Tempest tactics, techniques, and procedures (TTPs) observed in recent attack chains mapped to detection coverage.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-table is-style-regular"><table class="has-fixed-layout"><tbody><tr><td><strong>Tactic</strong><strong></strong>&nbsp;</td><td><strong>Technique</strong><strong></strong>&nbsp;</td><td><strong>Microsoft Protection Coverage (non-exhaustive)</strong><strong></strong>&nbsp;</td></tr><tr><td>Initial Access&nbsp;</td><td>Initiating password reset on target’s credentials&nbsp;</td><td>Unusual user password reset in your virtual machine; (MDC)&nbsp;</td></tr><tr><td>Discovery&nbsp;</td><td>Continuing environmental reconnaissance&nbsp;</td><td>Suspicious credential dump from NTDS.dit; (MDE)<br>Account enumeration reconnaissance; (MDI)<br>Network-mapping reconnaissance (DNS); (MDI)<br>User and IP address reconnaissance (SMB); (MDI)<br>User and Group membership reconnaissance (SAMR); (MDI)<br>Active Directory attributes reconnaissance (LDAP); (MDI)&nbsp;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Credential Access,&nbsp;&nbsp;Lateral Movement&nbsp;</td><td>Identifying Tier-0 assets&nbsp;</td><td>Mimikatz credential theft tool; (MDE)<br>ADExplorer collecting Active Directory information; (MDE)<br>Security principal reconnaissance (LDAP); (MDI)<br>Suspicious Azure role assignment detected; (MDC)<br>Suspicious elevate access operation; (MDC)<br>Suspicious domain added to Microsoft Entra ID; (MDA)<br>Suspicious domain trust modification following risky sign-in; (MDA)&nbsp;</td></tr><tr><td>Collecting additional credentials&nbsp;</td><td>Suspected DCSync attack (replication of directory services); (MDI)<br>Suspected AD FS DKM key read; (MDI)&nbsp;</td></tr><tr><td>Accessing enterprise environments with VPN and deploying VMs with tools to maintain access in compromised environments&nbsp;</td><td>&#8216;Ngrok&#8217; hacktool was prevented; (MDE)<br>&#8216;Chisel&#8217; hacktool was prevented; (MDE)<br>Possibly malicious use of proxy or tunneling tool; (MDE)<br>Possible Octo Tempest-related device registered (MDA)&nbsp;</td></tr><tr><td>Defense Evasion,&nbsp;Persistence&nbsp;</td><td>Leveraging EDR and management tooling&nbsp;</td><td>Tampering activity typical to ransomware attacks; (MDE)&nbsp;</td></tr><tr><td>Persistence,&nbsp;Execution&nbsp;</td><td>Installing a trusted backdoor&nbsp;</td><td>ADFS persistent backdoor; (MDE)&nbsp;</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2">Actions on Objectives&nbsp;</td><td>Staging and exfiltrating stolen data&nbsp;</td><td>Possible exfiltration of archived data; (MDE)<br>Data exfiltration over SMB; (MDI)&nbsp;</td></tr><tr><td>Deploying ransomware&nbsp;</td><td>‘DragonForce’ ransomware was prevented; (MDE)<br>Possible hands-on-keyboard pre-ransom activity; (MDE)&nbsp;</td></tr></tbody></table><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Note: The list is not exhaustive. A full list of available detections can be found in the Microsoft Defender portal.&nbsp;</figcaption></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="disrupting-octo-tempest-attacks">Disrupting Octo Tempest attacks&nbsp;&nbsp;</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><strong>Disrupt in-progress attacks with automatic attack disruption</strong>:<br>Attack disruption is Microsoft Defender’s <strong>unique, built-in self-defense capability</strong> that consumes multi-domain signals, the latest threat intelligence, and AI-powered machine learning models to <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/defender-xdr/automatic-attack-disruption" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">automatically predict and disrupt</a> an attacker’s next move by containing the compromised asset (user, device). This technology uses multiple potential indicators and behaviors, including all the detections listed above, possible Microsoft Entra ID sign-in attempts, <strong>possible Octo Tempest-related sign-in activities </strong>and correlate them across the Microsoft Defender workloads into a high-fidelity incident.&nbsp;</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Based on previous learnings from popular Octo Tempest techniques, attack disruption will automatically <strong>disable the user</strong> account used by Octo Tempest and revokes all existing active sessions by the compromised user.&nbsp;</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">While attack disruption can contain the attack by cutting off the attacker, it is critical for security operations center (SOC) teams to conduct incident response activities and post-incident analysis to help ensure the threat is fully contained and remediated.  </p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><strong>Investigate and hunt for Octo Tempest related activity</strong>:<br>Octo Tempest is infamously known for aggressive social engineering tactics, often impacting individuals with specific permissions to gain legitimate access and move laterally through networks. To help organizations identify these activities, customers can use Microsoft Defender’s advanced hunting capability to proactively investigate and respond to threats across their environment. Analysts can query across both first- and third-party data sources powered by Microsoft Defender XDR and Microsoft Sentinel. In addition to these tables, analysts can also use exposure insights from <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/security-exposure-management/microsoft-security-exposure-management" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Microsoft Security Exposure Management</a>. &nbsp;</p>



<div class="wp-block-buttons is-content-justification-center is-layout-flex wp-container-core-buttons-is-layout-5 wp-block-buttons-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-button"><a class="wp-block-button__link wp-element-button" href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/business/siem-and-xdr/microsoft-security-exposure-management" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Learn more about Microsoft Security Exposure Management</a></div>
</div>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Using advanced hunting and the Exposure Graph, defenders can proactively assess and hunt for the threat actor&#8217;s related activity and identify which users are most likely to be targeted and what will be the effect of a compromise, strengthening defenses before an attack occurs.  </p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="proactive-defense-against-octo-tempest">Proactive defense against Octo Tempest&nbsp;</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/business/siem-and-xdr/microsoft-security-exposure-management" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Microsoft Security Exposure Management</a>, available in the Microsoft Defender portal, equips security teams with capabilities such as critical asset protection, threat actor initiatives, and attack path analysis that enable security teams to proactively reduce exposure and mitigate the impact of Octo Tempest’s hybrid attack tactics.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="ensure-critical-assets-stay-protected">Ensure critical assets stay protected&nbsp;</h3>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Customers should ensure critical assets are <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/security-exposure-management/critical-asset-management" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">classified as critical</a> in the Microsoft Defender portal to generate relevant attack paths and recommendations in initiatives. Microsoft Defender automatically identifies critical devices in your environment, but teams should also create custom rules and expand critical asset identifiers to enhance protection.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="take-action-to-minimize-impact-with-initiatives">Take action to minimize impact with initiatives&nbsp;</h3>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/security-exposure-management/initiatives" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Exposure Management&#8217;s initiatives feature</a> provides goal-driven programs that unify key insights to help teams harden defenses and act fast on real threats. To address the most pressing risks related to Octo Tempest, we recommend organizations begin with the initiatives below:&nbsp;</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item"><strong>Octo Tempest Threat Initiative</strong>: Octo Tempest is known for tactics like extracting credentials from Local Security Authority Subsystem Service (LSASS) using tools like Mimikatz and signing in from attacker-controlled IPs—both of which can be mitigated through controls like attack surface reduction (ASR) rules and sign-in policies. This initiative brings these mitigations together into a focused program, mapping real-world attacker behaviors to actionable controls that help reduce exposure and disrupt attack paths before they escalate.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item"><strong>Ransomware Initiative</strong>: A broader initiative focused on reducing exposure to extortion-driven attacks through hardening identity, endpoint, and infrastructure layers. This will provide recommendations tailored for your organization. &nbsp;</li>
</ul>


<figure data-wp-context="{&quot;imageId&quot;:&quot;6882923cafdfa&quot;}" data-wp-interactive="core/image" class="wp-block-image aligncenter size-full wp-lightbox-container"><img decoding="async" data-wp-class--hide="state.isContentHidden" data-wp-class--show="state.isContentVisible" data-wp-init="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox" data-wp-on-async--load="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async-window--resize="callbacks.setButtonStyles" src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Actor-Profile.webp" alt="A screenshot of the Actor Profile: Octo Tempest [Preview] dashboard." class="wp-image-141192 webp-format" srcset="" data-orig-src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Actor-Profile.webp"><button
			class="lightbox-trigger"
			type="button"
			aria-haspopup="dialog"
			aria-label="Enlarge image: A screenshot of the Actor Profile: Octo Tempest [Preview] dashboard."
			data-wp-init="callbacks.initTriggerButton"
			data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox"
			data-wp-style--right="state.imageButtonRight"
			data-wp-style--top="state.imageButtonTop"
		>
			<svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="12" height="12" fill="none" viewBox="0 0 12 12">
				<path fill="#fff" d="M2 0a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v2h1.5V2a.5.5 0 0 1 .5-.5h2V0H2Zm2 10.5H2a.5.5 0 0 1-.5-.5V8H0v2a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h2v-1.5ZM8 12v-1.5h2a.5.5 0 0 0 .5-.5V8H12v2a2 2 0 0 1-2 2H8Zm2-12a2 2 0 0 1 2 2v2h-1.5V2a.5.5 0 0 0-.5-.5H8V0h2Z" />
			</svg>
		</button></figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="investigate-on-premises-and-hybrid-attack-paths">Investigate on-premises and hybrid attack paths</h3>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Security teams can use <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/security-exposure-management/work-attack-paths-overview" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">attack path analysis</a> to trace cross-domain threats—like those used by Octo Tempest—who’ve exploited the critical Entra Connect server to pivot into cloud workloads, escalate privileges, and expand their reach. Teams can use the ‘Chokepoint’ view in the attack path dashboard to highlight entities appearing in multiple paths, making it easy to filter for helpdesk-linked accounts, a known Octo target, and prioritize their remediation. &nbsp;</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Given Octo Tempest’s hybrid attack strategy, a representative attack path may look like this:&nbsp;</p>


<figure data-wp-context="{&quot;imageId&quot;:&quot;6882923cb2e79&quot;}" data-wp-interactive="core/image" class="wp-block-image size-full wp-lightbox-container"><img decoding="async" data-wp-class--hide="state.isContentHidden" data-wp-class--show="state.isContentVisible" data-wp-init="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox" data-wp-on-async--load="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async-window--resize="callbacks.setButtonStyles" src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/vulnerabilities.webp" alt="Device with high severity vulnerabilities allows lateral movement to azure key vault graph." class="wp-image-141193 webp-format" srcset="" data-orig-src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/vulnerabilities.webp"><button
			class="lightbox-trigger"
			type="button"
			aria-haspopup="dialog"
			aria-label="Enlarge image: Device with high severity vulnerabilities allows lateral movement to azure key vault graph."
			data-wp-init="callbacks.initTriggerButton"
			data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox"
			data-wp-style--right="state.imageButtonRight"
			data-wp-style--top="state.imageButtonTop"
		>
			<svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="12" height="12" fill="none" viewBox="0 0 12 12">
				<path fill="#fff" d="M2 0a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v2h1.5V2a.5.5 0 0 1 .5-.5h2V0H2Zm2 10.5H2a.5.5 0 0 1-.5-.5V8H0v2a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h2v-1.5ZM8 12v-1.5h2a.5.5 0 0 0 .5-.5V8H12v2a2 2 0 0 1-2 2H8Zm2-12a2 2 0 0 1 2 2v2h-1.5V2a.5.5 0 0 0-.5-.5H8V0h2Z" />
			</svg>
		</button></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="recommendations">Recommendations&nbsp;</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">In today’s threat landscape, proactive security is essential. By following security best practices, you reduce the attack surface and limit the potential impact of adversaries like Octo Tempest. Microsoft recommends implementing the following to help strengthen your overall posture and stay ahead of threats:&nbsp;</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="identity-security-recommendations">Identity security recommendations&nbsp;</h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item">Ensure multifactor authentication is enabled for all users: Adding more authentication methods, such as the <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/entra/identity/authentication/how-to-enable-authenticator-passkey" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Microsoft Authenticator app</a> or a phone number, increases the level of protection if one factor is compromised.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Enable <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/entra/id-protection/overview-identity-protection" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Microsoft Entra ID Identity Protection</a> sign-in risk policies: Turning on the sign-in risk policy ensures that suspicious sign-ins are challenged for.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Ensure <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/entra/identity/conditional-access/policy-admin-phish-resistant-mfa" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">phishing-resistant multifactor authentication strength</a> is required for Administrators.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Ensure <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/defender-for-cloud/recommendations-reference-identity-access" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Microsoft Azure overprovisioned identities</a> should have only the necessary permissions.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Enable <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/entra/id-governance/privileged-identity-management/pim-configure" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Microsoft Entra Privileged Identity Management</a> as well as other protective measures to mitigate the risk of unnecessary or unauthorized access.</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="endpoint-security-recommendations">Endpoint security recommendations&nbsp;</h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item">Enable Microsoft Defender Antivirus <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/defender-endpoint/linux-preferences" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cloud-delivered protection for Linux</a>.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Turn on Microsoft Defender Antivirus <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/defender-endpoint/microsoft-defender-endpoint-linux" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">real-time protection for Linux</a>.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Enable Microsoft Defender for Endpoint <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/defender-endpoint/edr-in-block-mode" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">EDR in block mode</a> to block post breach malicious behavior on the device through behavior blocking and containment capabilities.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Turn on <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/defender-endpoint/prevent-changes-to-security-settings-with-tamper-protection" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">tamper protection</a> that essentially prevents Microsoft Defender for Endpoint (your security settings) from being modified.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Block credential stealing from the Windows local security authority subsystem: <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/defender-endpoint/attack-surface-reduction-rules-reference" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Attack surface reduction (ASR)</a> rules are the most effective method for blocking the most common attack techniques being used in cyber-attacks and malicious software.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Turn on <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/security/identity-protection/credential-guard/configure?tabs=intune" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Microsoft Defender Credential Guard</a> to isolate secrets so that only privileged system software can access them.</li>
</ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="cloud-security-recommendations">Cloud security recommendations&nbsp;</h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item">Key Vaults should have <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/key-vault/general/key-vault-recovery?tabs=azure-powershell" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">purge protection enabled</a> to prevent immediate, irreversible deletion of vaults and secrets.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">To reduce risks of overly permissive inbound rules on virtual machines’ management ports, <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/defender-for-cloud/just-in-time-access-overview?tabs=defender-for-container-arch-aks" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">enable just-in-time (JIT)</a> network access control.&nbsp;</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Microsoft Defender for Cloud recommends encrypting data with customer-managed keys (CMK) to support strict compliance or regulatory requirements. To reduce risk and increase control, <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/defender-for-cloud/enable-agentless-scanning-vms" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">enable CMK</a> to manage your own encryption keys through Microsoft Azure Key Vault.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item"><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/key-vault/general/howto-logging?tabs=azure-cli" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Enable logs in Azure Key Vault</a> and retain them for up to a year. This enables you to recreate activity trails for investigation purposes when a security incident occurs or your network is compromised.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item"><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/azure/backup/backup-during-vm-creation" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Microsoft Azure Backup</a> should be enabled for virtual machines to protect the data on your Microsoft Azure virtual machines, and to create recovery points that are stored in geo-redundant recovery vaults.</li>
</ul>



<div class="wp-block-bloginabox-theme-promotional">
	
<div class="promotional promotional--has-media promotional--media-right">
	<div class="promotional__wrapper">
		<div class="promotional__content-wrapper">
			<div class="promotional__content">
				

<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="microsoft-defender">Microsoft Defender</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Comprehensive threat prevention, detection and response capabilities for everyone.</p>



<div class="wp-block-buttons is-layout-flex wp-block-buttons-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-button"><a data-bi-an="Global CTA" data-bi-ct="cta link" data-bi-id="cta-block" class="wp-block-button__link wp-element-button" href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/business/microsoft-defender?msockid=27b7b3bc5be566bc06c9a5a05a7a679d">Discover more</a></div>
</div>

			</div>
		</div>
					<div class="promotional__media-wrapper">
				<div class="promotional__media">
											<img decoding="async" width="2560" height="1664" src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/Win17_CDOC_1533-scaled.jpg" class="attachment-full size-full" alt="A group of people sitting at computers" loading="lazy" srcset="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/Win17_CDOC_1533-scaled.jpg 2560w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/Win17_CDOC_1533-300x195.jpg 300w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/Win17_CDOC_1533-1024x666.jpg 1024w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/Win17_CDOC_1533-768x499.jpg 768w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/Win17_CDOC_1533-1536x998.jpg 1536w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/Win17_CDOC_1533-2048x1331.jpg 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 2560px) 100vw, 2560px" />									</div>
			</div>
			</div>
</div>
</div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="explore-security-solutions">Explore security solutions</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">​​To learn more about Microsoft Security solutions, <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/business" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">visit our website</a>. Bookmark the <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/security/blog/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Microsoft Security blog</a> to keep up with our expert coverage on security matters.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Also, follow us on <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/showcase/microsoft-security/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Microsoft Security LinkedIn</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/@MSFTSecurity" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">@MSFTSecurity</a> on X for the latest news and updates on cybersecurity.&nbsp;</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/2025/07/16/protecting-customers-from-octo-tempest-attacks-across-multiple-industries/">Protecting customers from Octo Tempest attacks across multiple industries</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog">Microsoft Security Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Improving IT efficiency with Microsoft Security Copilot in Microsoft Intune and Microsoft Entra</title>
		<link>https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/2025/07/14/improving-it-efficiency-with-microsoft-security-copilot-in-microsoft-intune-and-microsoft-entra/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Dorothy Li]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 14 Jul 2025 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/?p=141146</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Announcing the general availability of Microsoft Security Copilot capabilities for IT with Microsoft Intune and Microsoft Entra, offering AI-powered efficiency and enhanced security for your operations.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/2025/07/14/improving-it-efficiency-with-microsoft-security-copilot-in-microsoft-intune-and-microsoft-entra/">Improving IT efficiency with Microsoft Security Copilot in Microsoft Intune and Microsoft Entra</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog">Microsoft Security Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p class="wp-block-paragraph">When Microsoft introduced <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/business/ai-machine-learning/microsoft-security-copilot">Microsoft Security Copilot</a> last year, our vision was to empower organizations with generative AI that helps security and IT teams simplify operations and respond faster. Since then, we’ve continuously innovated and learned alongside our customers. They consistently tell us that practitioners love it when Copilot is built directly into the tools they use every day.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">That’s why we’re focused on delivering deeply integrated, scenario-based experiences that align with Zero Trust principles, making it easier for IT and security professionals to ask questions, take action, and gain insights directly within their existing workflows. These experiences not only reduce friction but also help IT teams stay in flow, making smarter decisions faster and with greater confidence. And the impact is real: organizations using Security Copilot have seen a <a href="https://cdn-dynmedia-1.microsoft.com/is/content/microsoftcorp/microsoft/final/en-us/microsoft-brand/documents/Copilot_productivity_external_Spring2025_042125_v3_remediated.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">54% reduction in time to resolve device policy conflicts</a>, and a 22.8% drop in alerts per incident within three months of adoption, freeing up teams to focus on more strategic work.</p>



<div class="wp-block-buttons is-content-justification-center is-layout-flex wp-container-core-buttons-is-layout-7 wp-block-buttons-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-button has-custom-width wp-block-button__width-75"><a class="wp-block-button__link wp-element-button" href="https://www.microsoft.com/security/business/ai-machine-learning/microsoft-security-copilot">Get started with Microsoft Security Copilot</a></div>
</div>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">We’re excited to announce <strong>the Security Copilot capabilities in <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/security/business/microsoft-intune">Microsoft Intune</a> and <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/security/business/microsoft-entra">Microsoft Entra</a> have moved from preview to general availability</strong>. This milestone reflects the critical role Intune and Entra play in modern security strategies, serving as the foundation for implementing a Zero Trust model. Intune enforces device compliance, app protection, and endpoint privilege management, while Entra governs identity access with Conditional Access policies and granular authentication controls. Together, they create a unified security posture that aligns with <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/security/business/zero-trust">Zero Trust principles</a> across devices, users, applications, and even agents. Security Copilot amplifies this foundation by providing AI-assisted guidance, autonomous agents, and insights accessible through natural language, helping IT teams scale operations, accelerate skilling, and proactively remediate threats at machine speed.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="reimagining-it-workflows-with-security-copilot-in-intune">Reimagining IT workflows with Security Copilot in Intune</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">IT administrators often face a daily flood of data, alerts, and configuration details, making it difficult to quickly find the right information and act with confidence. AI is changing how people work, and Copilot in Intune is evolving how IT admins interact with and act on their endpoint management data. The Security Copilot in Intune general availability release introduces a brand new, Copilot-assisted data exploration capability. IT admins now have <a href="https://aka.ms/Intune/CopilotJuly2025">a dedicated page</a> in the Intune admin center to ask Copilot for the data they need, take action, and complete endpoint management tasks, all without leaving their workflow. This capability allows admins to extract insights across Intune domains—devices, apps, security policies, users, compliance data, app configurations, and more—and act on it using its deep integration into the Intune functionality they are familiar with. It represents the first step in a foundational shift from traditional reporting and queries to Copilot-powered investigation and IT-empowered action.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">This new Security Copilot capability is designed to simplify the most time-consuming IT workflows, like assessing security posture, managing updates, troubleshooting issues, and generating custom reports. Whether it’s identifying non-compliant devices, tracking patch failures, previewing policy impact, or automating remediation, Copilot brings together the data and actions IT needs in one place.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Admins can ask natural language questions like, “Show me devices that are not on the latest version of Windows and Office,” or “Which of my Endpoint Privilege Management rules are in conflict and what are the source profiles?” and take action instantly, without switching context.</p>


<figure data-wp-context="{&quot;imageId&quot;:&quot;6882923cc4af0&quot;}" data-wp-interactive="core/image" class="wp-block-image size-large wp-lightbox-container"><img decoding="async" data-wp-class--hide="state.isContentHidden" data-wp-class--show="state.isContentVisible" data-wp-init="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox" data-wp-on-async--load="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async-window--resize="callbacks.setButtonStyles" src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture1-1-1024x527.webp" alt="A screenshot of the Intune admin center with a new left navigation option to explore Intune data.  Options for administrators to data across multiple workload categories such as Device compliance, apps, devices, app configuration and protection. " class="wp-image-141150 webp-format" srcset="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture1-1-1024x527.webp 1024w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture1-1-300x154.webp 300w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture1-1-768x395.webp 768w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture1-1-1536x790.webp 1536w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture1-1.webp 1676w" data-orig-src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture1-1-1024x527.webp"><button
			class="lightbox-trigger"
			type="button"
			aria-haspopup="dialog"
			aria-label="Enlarge image: A screenshot of the Intune admin center with a new left navigation option to explore Intune data.  Options for administrators to data across multiple workload categories such as Device compliance, apps, devices, app configuration and protection. "
			data-wp-init="callbacks.initTriggerButton"
			data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox"
			data-wp-style--right="state.imageButtonRight"
			data-wp-style--top="state.imageButtonTop"
		>
			<svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="12" height="12" fill="none" viewBox="0 0 12 12">
				<path fill="#fff" d="M2 0a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v2h1.5V2a.5.5 0 0 1 .5-.5h2V0H2Zm2 10.5H2a.5.5 0 0 1-.5-.5V8H0v2a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h2v-1.5ZM8 12v-1.5h2a.5.5 0 0 0 .5-.5V8H12v2a2 2 0 0 1-2 2H8Zm2-12a2 2 0 0 1 2 2v2h-1.5V2a.5.5 0 0 0-.5-.5H8V0h2Z" />
			</svg>
		</button></figure>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><em>Figure 1. New experience to explore your Intune data <em>with Copilot assistance</em></em> <em>across workloads.</em></p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">The new Explorer experience also includes support for Windows 365 Cloud PCs, giving IT administrators a consistent way to view and act on device details across both cloud and physical endpoints. We are excited to share that <strong>in the coming weeks, we’ll introduce additional AI capabilities in Intune with Copilot assistance for Windows 365</strong>, offering insights into Cloud PC connectivity and connection quality, licensing optimization, and performance issues tied to compute resources. These capabilities build on the momentum of virtual computing and the ability to stream Windows from the Cloud, enhancing the IT experience and delivering even more endpoint management value—especially for Windows-based environments.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">The general availability release of Security Copilot in Intune also provides chat-based contextual assistance and includes integration with core and Microsoft Intune Suite solutions. Intune Advanced Analytics multiple device query (MDQ), and Copilot help admins write detailed Kusto Query Language (KQL) queries and Endpoint Privilege Management with Copilot assesses app risks for admins to make informed decisions before approving Windows users’ elevation requests. And with the <a href="https://aka.ms/CopilotSurfaceMgmtPortalBlog" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Surface Management Portal</a> in Intune, Copilot provides unified visibility and controls for IT across Surface devices, further strengthening security posture and streamlining operations.</p>



<div class="wp-block-buttons is-content-justification-center is-layout-flex wp-container-core-buttons-is-layout-8 wp-block-buttons-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-button has-custom-width wp-block-button__width-100"><a class="wp-block-button__link wp-element-button" href="https://www.microsoft.com/security/business/microsoft-intune">Microsoft Intune: Empower IT. Protect endpoints. Optimize with AI.</a></div>
</div>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Just as Security Copilot is transforming endpoint management in Intune, it’s also reshaping how identity is managed in Microsoft Entra.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="security-copilot-in-entra-brings-clarity-and-speed-to-identity-security">Security Copilot in Entra brings clarity and speed to identity security</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Identity environments evolve daily—new user, apps, and permissions are constantly introduced, making it difficult for IT and identity admins to keep policies up to date and user access properly governed. Manual investigations done the traditional way can be very time-consuming and reactive, giving cyberattackers more time to exploit gaps. With more than 600 million identity-based attacks happening daily, organizations can’t afford slow, manual investigations or infrequent policy reviews.<sup>1</sup></p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><a href="https://aka.ms/EntraCopilotGANews2025">Security Copilot in Microsoft Entra, now generally available</a>, brings AI-assisted reasoning, natural language prompts, and real-time insights across your identity and access estate, all within the Microsoft Entra admin center. We’ve made major enhancements to improve performance, scalability, and accuracy, enabling Security Copilot to better understand user intent, handle more complex questions, and deliver clearer answers.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">&nbsp;We’ve also expanded coverage to support a broader set of real-world identity scenarios. Copilot in Entra now helps admins investigate users, troubleshoot sign-ins, manage access reviews and entitlements, monitor tenant health and service-level agreement (SLAs), optimize license usage, and analyze role assignments and recommendations—all grounded in Microsoft Graph data.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Admins can now ask natural language questions like, “Which enterprise applications have credentials about to expire?” and “What role does the user have?” to quickly surface insights and take action. Whether it’s reviewing access packages, identifying risky apps, or checking license availability, Security Copilot in Entra helps teams move faster, stay ahead of cyberthreats, and focus on what matters most.</p>



<div class="wp-block-buttons is-content-justification-center is-layout-flex wp-container-core-buttons-is-layout-9 wp-block-buttons-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-button has-custom-width wp-block-button__width-100"><a class="wp-block-button__link wp-element-button" href="https://www.microsoft.com/security/business/microsoft-entra">Microsoft Entra: Comprehensive identity and network access solutions</a></div>
</div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="purpose-built-agents-for-real-world-it-challenges">Purpose-built agents for real-world IT challenges</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">At Microsoft Secure 2025, as part of our vision to deliver an <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/2025/03/24/microsoft-unveils-microsoft-security-copilot-agents-and-new-protections-for-ai/">AI-first, end-to-end security platform</a>, Microsoft announced <a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/blog/SecurityCopilotBlog/automate-cybersecurity-at-scale-with-microsoft-security-copilot-agents/4394675/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">11 AI-powered Security Copilot agents</a> that are seamlessly integrated with Microsoft Security and partner solutions. These agents autonomously handle high-volume, high-value tasks, learn from feedback, adapt to workflows, and operate securely, reflecting our commitment to helping organizations achieve what was previously impossible—at machine speed.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Today marks a meaningful milestone in our journey toward an AI-first, end-to-end security platform: we’re announcing the general availability of the Conditional Access Optimization Agent in Microsoft Entra. This launch brings AI-powered automation to IT and security operations, helping teams bring proactive protection directly into identity workflows.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">The Conditional Access Optimization Agent runs autonomously, scanning your environment for gaps, overlaps, and outdated policy assignments. It then recommends precise, one-click remediations to help close the gaps fast, turning reactive cleanup into proactive defense.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">The Conditional Access Optimization Agent provides:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item"><strong>Autonomous protection, every day</strong>—Automatically detects newly created users or apps not covered by Conditional Access policies, reducing risk between manual audits.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item"><strong>Real-time, explainable decisions</strong>—Every recommendation includes a plain-language summary and visual activity map showing how the agent reached its conclusion.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item"><strong>Continuous adaptability to your organization’s needs</strong>—Support for custom business rules, the agent can learn based on your natural-language feedback (for example, excluding break-glass accounts).</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item"><strong>Full auditability</strong>—Agent actions like install, enable and disable, and recommendations are recorded in the audit log for compliance and operational transparency.</li>
</ul>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">With the Conditional Access Optimization Agent, policy coverage becomes continuous. You gain daily protection, policy clarity, and built-in expertise without the manual lift. As one security leader put it:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote has-quote-default-font-size is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p class="has-body-large-font-size wp-block-paragraph"><em>“The Conditional Access Optimization Agent is like having a security analyst on call 24/7. It proactively identifies gaps in our Conditional Access policies and ensures every user is protected from day one, and with report-only mode and AI-driven recommendations, we can test and refine access policies without disruption. It’s a secure path to innovation that every chief information security officer can trust.&#8221;</em> </p>



<p class="has-body-large-font-size wp-block-paragraph">—Julian Rasmussen, Senior consultant and Partner, Point Taken, Microsoft MVP</p>
</blockquote>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="step-into-the-future-of-it-with-security-copilot">Step into the future of IT with Security Copilot</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">We’re in a new era of AI that has implications for IT operations and security. Now with <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/business/ai-machine-learning/microsoft-security-copilot">Microsoft Security Copilot</a> in Intune and Entra, you can make your organization future-ready with AI solutions that help organizations transform IT and security at machine speed.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">As part of our ongoing commitment to enhancing the embedded experience of Security Copilot across Microsoft Security products, we’re excited to introduce a new <a href="https://securitycopilot.microsoft.com/calculator" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">in-portal capacity calculator</a> available in the Security Copilot standalone experience (Azure account required). This tool allows organizations to estimate the number of Security Compute Units (SCUs) they may need based on the number of Security Copilot users in each Microsoft Security product. Users can generate a quick estimate, providing a practical starting point for capacity planning. SCU allocations can be adjusted at any time as real-world usage patterns emerge. <a href="https://aka.ms/scp-mws" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Learn more</a>.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Explore more use cases for IT and identity admins in the Security Copilot <a href="https://adoption.microsoft.com/security-copilot/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">adoption hub</a>. Explore Copilot in Intune and Entra and take these steps to learn more:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item"><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/copilot/security/get-started-security-copilot" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Get started</strong> with Microsoft Security Copilot</a>.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item"><strong>Learn more</strong> about how to apply <a href="https://adoption.microsoft.com/microsoft-security/intune/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Microsoft Intune</a> and <a href="https://adoption.microsoft.com/en-us/microsoft-security/entra/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Microsoft Entra</a> to your program.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item"><strong>Connect with your Microsoft representative</strong> to schedule a demo or get more information.</li>
</ul>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">To learn more about Microsoft Security solutions, visit our <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/business">website.</a> Bookmark the <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/security/blog/">Security blog</a> to keep up with our expert coverage on security matters. Also, follow us on LinkedIn (<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/showcase/microsoft-security/">Microsoft Security</a>) and X (<a href="https://twitter.com/@MSFTSecurity">@MSFTSecurity</a>) for the latest news and updates on cybersecurity.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><sup>1</sup><a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/security-insider/intelligence-reports/microsoft-digital-defense-report-2024?msockid=27b7b3bc5be566bc06c9a5a05a7a679d" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Microsoft Digital Defense Report 2024</a>.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><em>The data, insights, and events in this report represent July 2023 through June 2024 (Microsoft fiscal year 2024), unless otherwise noted.</em></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/2025/07/14/improving-it-efficiency-with-microsoft-security-copilot-in-microsoft-intune-and-microsoft-entra/">Improving IT efficiency with Microsoft Security Copilot in Microsoft Intune and Microsoft Entra</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog">Microsoft Security Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>​​Forrester names Microsoft a Leader in the 2025 Zero Trust Platforms Wave™ report</title>
		<link>https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/2025/07/10/forrester-names-microsoft-a-leader-in-the-2025-zero-trust-platforms-wave-report/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Joy Chik and Vasu Jakkal]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 10 Jul 2025 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/?p=141122</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Employing a Zero Trust strategy is an effective way to modernize security infrastructure to protect against ever evolving security challenges.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/2025/07/10/forrester-names-microsoft-a-leader-in-the-2025-zero-trust-platforms-wave-report/">​​Forrester names Microsoft a Leader in the 2025 Zero Trust Platforms Wave™ report</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog">Microsoft Security Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p class="wp-block-paragraph">We are proud to share that Forrester has named Microsoft a Leader in <a href="https://reprint.forrester.com/reprints/the-forrester-wavetm-zero-trust-platforms-q3-2025-43d86381" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">The Forrester Wave™: Zero Trust Platforms, Q3 2025 report</a>, ranking us highest in the strategy category.</p>


<figure class="wp-block-image aligncenter size-large"><img decoding="async" src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Image_Zero-Trust-Platforms-Q3-2025-1-799x1024.webp" alt="The Forrester Wave: Zero Trust Platforms, Q 3 2025 report." class="wp-image-141166 webp-format" srcset="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Image_Zero-Trust-Platforms-Q3-2025-1-799x1024.webp 799w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Image_Zero-Trust-Platforms-Q3-2025-1-234x300.webp 234w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Image_Zero-Trust-Platforms-Q3-2025-1-768x984.webp 768w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Image_Zero-Trust-Platforms-Q3-2025-1-1199x1536.webp 1199w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Image_Zero-Trust-Platforms-Q3-2025-1.webp 1240w" data-orig-src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Image_Zero-Trust-Platforms-Q3-2025-1-799x1024.webp"></figure>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">With so many strong vendors and solutions in the Zero Trust space, you need solid data to make the right choice for your organization. That’s why Forrester’s analysis matters. They provide detailed comparisons of vendor capabilities and strategic vision, helping security leaders evaluate which platforms are best equipped to meet today’s evolving challenges.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Your decision matters now more than ever. The security landscape is evolving rapidly with the rise of generative and agentic AI—where intelligent agents can create and collaborate with other agents, collaborate autonomously, and scale faster than traditional models can keep up. Systems once built for human identities must now manage a growing web of machine identities, each with its own access and risk profile.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">In this landscape, adhering to the principles of Zero Trust is critical for protecting sensitive resources, so you can:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item">Expand visibility across your digital environment to reduce security vulnerabilities.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Secure your most critical assets while ensuring compliance.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Deploy generative AI with confidence.</li>
</ul>



<div class="wp-block-buttons is-content-justification-center is-layout-flex wp-container-core-buttons-is-layout-10 wp-block-buttons-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-button"><a class="wp-block-button__link wp-element-button" href="https://reprint.forrester.com/reprints/the-forrester-wavetm-zero-trust-platforms-q3-2025-43d86381" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Read the full Forrester Wave™: Zero Trust Platforms, Q3 2025 report to learn more</a></div>
</div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="microsoft-s-end-to-end-integrated-approach-to-zero-trust">Microsoft’s end-to-end, integrated approach to Zero Trust</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">The Forrester report cited our vision for proactive security architecture powered by innovative AI agents that automate complex security, IT, and productivity tasks. But what we believe really caught their attention was our integrated approach—how we bring together capabilities across security, compliance, identity, device management, and privacy, all informed by more than 84 trillion threat signals a day.<sup><em>1</em></sup> As they noted, &#8220;Microsoft excels at tool consolidation and integration, helping reduce costs and overhead.&#8221;</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Customers interviewed for the report recognized that our &#8220;deep cross-platform integration&#8221; delivers &#8220;real business value&#8221; without making customers stitch different solutions together manually. This integration spans the entire Microsoft Security portfolio—Microsoft Defender, Microsoft Purview, Microsoft Intune, Microsoft Sentinel, and Microsoft Entra—to provide a unified platform that secures identities, endpoints, data, apps, infrastructure, and AI. At the heart of this integration are the strong identity management capabilities of Microsoft Entra, which Forrester noted for &#8220;deliver[ing] effective least-privilege access enforcement&#8221; while enabling data security controls and endpoint management.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Picture a typical attack pattern. Malicious activity in an on-premises system might be detected by Defender for Identity, a compromised device flagged by Defender for Endpoint, and risky insider behavior identified by Purview. These signals converge in Entra conditional access, your centralized policy engine, enabling real-time, risk-based access controls that adapt to emerging threats and, when necessary, block access automatically.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Powered by AI and threat intelligence, our unified security platform surfaces high-priority incidents and recommends next actions, transforming security from a collection of tools into a cohesive defense. You can work within our unified platform to prevent, detect, and respond to incidents across a single integrated system—no jumping between dashboards or correlating signals manually. All of this comes together with Microsoft Security Exposure Management to give full visibility into all your assets and help you proactively reduce risk.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">An integrated approach doesn&#8217;t mean using only Microsoft solutions. We believe security is a team sport. In fact, the Forrester report recognized the maturity and scale of our global partner ecosystem. We&#8217;ve invested heavily in these partnerships because they provide additional signals and specialized protections that make the entire security community stronger. The report also cited our standout community, which provides education, training, and guidance on building Zero Trust architectures to ensure customers have the support they need at every step.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="our-commitment-to-customers-and-the-industry">Our commitment to customers and the industry</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Through our <a href="https://aka.ms/securefutureinitiative" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Secure Future Initiative</a>, we continuously evaluate and strengthen our own security posture, improve the security of our products to better protect customers, and share <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/2025/05/15/how-the-microsoft-secure-future-initiative-brings-zero-trust-to-life/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">progress and learnings</a> with the industry. We are also committed to standards, guidelines, and best practices from the National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST), The Open Group, the Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency (CISA), and MITRE—not as compliance checkboxes, but because they provide proven frameworks and common vocabulary for implementing effective security.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="take-action-to-improve-your-security-posture">Take action to improve your security posture</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Threats are evolving faster than ever, but so are defenses. With the right Zero Trust security strategy, you can embrace AI&#8217;s transformative power while keeping your organization secure. Microsoft’s leadership in <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/security/business/zero-trust" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Zero Trust</a>, as reflected for us in the latest Forrester Wave™, highlights our commitment to helping you meet these security demands.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">For more information on this recognition, check out the full <a href="https://reprint.forrester.com/reprints/the-forrester-wavetm-zero-trust-platforms-q3-2025-43d86381" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Forrester Wave™: Zero Trust Platforms, Q3 2025 report</a>.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Ready to evaluate your Zero Trust readiness for the AI era? Start with our <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/security/zero-trust/zero-trust-assessment-progress-tracking-resources" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Zero Trust assessment</a>, host an <a href="https://aka.ms/ZTWorkshop" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">implementation workshop</a>, or dive into our step-by-step <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/business/zero-trust" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">implementation guides</a>.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">To learn more about Microsoft Security solutions, visit our&nbsp;<a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/business" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">website.</a>&nbsp;Bookmark the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.microsoft.com/security/blog/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Security blog</a>&nbsp;to keep up with our expert coverage on security matters. Also, follow us on LinkedIn (<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/showcase/microsoft-security/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Microsoft Security</a>) and X (<a href="https://twitter.com/@MSFTSecurity" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">@MSFTSecurity</a>)&nbsp;for the latest news and updates on cybersecurity.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><em>The Forrester Wave™: Zero Trust Platforms, Q3 2025, Joshep Blankenship, Faith Born, and Peter Harrison. July 10, 2025. </em></p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><em>Forrester does not endorse any company, product, brand, or service included in its research publications and does not advise any person to select the products or services of any company or brand based on the ratings included in such publications. Information is based on the best available resources. Opinions reflect judgment at the time and are subject to change. For more information, read about Forrester’s objectivity </em><a href="https://www.forrester.com/about-us/objectivity/"><em>here </em></a>.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><em><sup>1</sup>Based on Microsoft internal data. Accurate as of July 2025</em>.</p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/2025/07/10/forrester-names-microsoft-a-leader-in-the-2025-zero-trust-platforms-wave-report/">​​Forrester names Microsoft a Leader in the 2025 Zero Trust Platforms Wave™ report</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog">Microsoft Security Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Microsoft expands Zero Trust workshop to cover network, SecOps, and more</title>
		<link>https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/2025/07/09/microsoft-expands-zero-trust-workshop-to-cover-network-secops-and-more/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Rob Lefferts]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 16:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/?p=140561</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The Microsoft Zero Trust workshop has been expanded to cover all six pillars of Zero Trust security, providing a comprehensive guide for organizations to modernize their security posture. </p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/2025/07/09/microsoft-expands-zero-trust-workshop-to-cover-network-secops-and-more/">Microsoft expands Zero Trust workshop to cover network, SecOps, and more</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog">Microsoft Security Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="building-on-identity-devices-and-data-the-workshop-now-covers-network-infrastructure-and-secops">Building on identity, devices, and data, the workshop now covers network, infrastructure, and SecOps</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">As the nature of cyberthreats and security challenges evolve, organizations have coalesced around a Zero Trust architecture as the approach to modernize their end-to-end security adoption and posture. In November 2024, we introduced a preview of the Microsoft Zero Trust workshop that focused on the traditional “secure access” pillars (identity, data, and devices). We are announcing the expansion of the <a href="https://aka.ms/ZTWorkshop">Zero Trust workshop</a> to cover the additional technical pillars of Zero Trust—assisting customers on strategies that may contribute to securing their network, infrastructure, and connecting all these elements with security operations (SecOps). We invite you to take a look at the newly expanded workshop, give it a try, and share feedback with us as you continue on your end-to-end security modernization journey.</p>



<div class="wp-block-buttons is-content-justification-center is-layout-flex wp-container-core-buttons-is-layout-11 wp-block-buttons-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-button has-custom-width wp-block-button__width-75"><a class="wp-block-button__link wp-element-button" href="https://aka.ms/ZTWorkshop">Learn more about the new Microsoft Zero Trust workshop</a></div>
</div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="the-need-for-a-zero-trust-workshop">The need for a Zero Trust workshop</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Customers have consistently told us that they see <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/security/business/zero-trust">Zero Trust</a> as a strategic foundation for how they approach and run a modern security practice. However, customers have also shared that they need help and guidance understanding how their security products could help them achieve a Zero Trust vision, and how they can measure how far along they are on their journey to implement Zero Trust.</p>


<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture1-1024x584.webp" alt="Graph showing which areas customers want help with when implementing Zero Trust." class="wp-image-140935 webp-format" srcset="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture1-1024x584.webp 1024w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture1-300x171.webp 300w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture1-768x438.webp 768w, https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture1.webp 1202w" data-orig-src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture1-1024x584.webp"></figure>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><em>Figure 1. Top areas customers ask for help with in advancing their Zero Trust journey.</em></p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Last year, we introduced the Microsoft Zero Trust workshop as a valuable resource for our customers and partners. By guiding participants through a comprehensive journey across the pillars of Zero Trust, this workshop aims to assist with strategies to deploy security products and features. It outlines the priority of tasks, provides a framework to track progress, and allows participants to measure their advancements against established benchmarks in subsequent evaluations.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">In the initial launch, we focused on three key pillars of the Zero Trust framework:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item"><strong>Identity</strong>: Ensuring that the right people have access to the right resources through robust authentication and authorization mechanisms.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item"><strong>Devices</strong>: Securing endpoints to prevent unauthorized access and to ensure compliance with organizational policies.</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item"><strong>Data</strong>: Protecting sensitive information through encryption, data classification, and access control.</li>
</ul>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">This foundational approach emphasizes strategies on preventative security capabilities and access control to resources. These pillars served as the cornerstone for ways in which organizations could better secure their systems against unauthorized access and data breaches. Since its launch, the workshop has been downloaded more than 3,000 times by customers to enhance their end-to-end security posture. More than 150 Microsoft Partners trained to use it as well, with several adopting it as a delivery mechanism.</p>



<div class="wp-block-buttons is-content-justification-center is-layout-flex wp-container-core-buttons-is-layout-12 wp-block-buttons-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-button has-custom-width wp-block-button__width-75"><a class="wp-block-button__link wp-element-button" href="https://aka.ms/ZTWorkshop">Get started with the expanded Microsoft Zero Trust workshop</a></div>
</div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="access-control-posture-and-detection-and-response">Access control, posture, and detection and response</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">We’re proud to announce that we have expanded the Zero Trust workshop from three Zero Trust pillars to cover a total of six pillars, adding: </p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item"><strong>Networking</strong>: Implementing micro-segmentation, real-time threat detection, and secure access to network resources to ensure comprehensive network security.</li>
</ul>


<figure data-wp-context="{&quot;imageId&quot;:&quot;6882923ce44f6&quot;}" data-wp-interactive="core/image" class="wp-block-image size-full wp-lightbox-container"><img decoding="async" data-wp-class--hide="state.isContentHidden" data-wp-class--show="state.isContentVisible" data-wp-init="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox" data-wp-on-async--load="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async-window--resize="callbacks.setButtonStyles" src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture2.webp" alt="Image of the network pillar of the Zero Trust Workshop." class="wp-image-140936 webp-format" srcset="" data-orig-src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture2.webp"><button
			class="lightbox-trigger"
			type="button"
			aria-haspopup="dialog"
			aria-label="Enlarge image: Image of the network pillar of the Zero Trust Workshop."
			data-wp-init="callbacks.initTriggerButton"
			data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox"
			data-wp-style--right="state.imageButtonRight"
			data-wp-style--top="state.imageButtonTop"
		>
			<svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="12" height="12" fill="none" viewBox="0 0 12 12">
				<path fill="#fff" d="M2 0a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v2h1.5V2a.5.5 0 0 1 .5-.5h2V0H2Zm2 10.5H2a.5.5 0 0 1-.5-.5V8H0v2a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h2v-1.5ZM8 12v-1.5h2a.5.5 0 0 0 .5-.5V8H12v2a2 2 0 0 1-2 2H8Zm2-12a2 2 0 0 1 2 2v2h-1.5V2a.5.5 0 0 0-.5-.5H8V0h2Z" />
			</svg>
		</button></figure>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item"><strong>Infrastructure</strong>: Securing cloud and on-premises infrastructure through robust configurations, access management, and continuous monitoring.</li>
</ul>


<figure data-wp-context="{&quot;imageId&quot;:&quot;6882923ce74eb&quot;}" data-wp-interactive="core/image" class="wp-block-image size-full wp-lightbox-container"><img decoding="async" data-wp-class--hide="state.isContentHidden" data-wp-class--show="state.isContentVisible" data-wp-init="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox" data-wp-on-async--load="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async-window--resize="callbacks.setButtonStyles" src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture3.webp" alt="Image of the infrastructure pillar of the Zero Trust workshop." class="wp-image-140937 webp-format" srcset="" data-orig-src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture3.webp"><button
			class="lightbox-trigger"
			type="button"
			aria-haspopup="dialog"
			aria-label="Enlarge image: Image of the infrastructure pillar of the Zero Trust workshop."
			data-wp-init="callbacks.initTriggerButton"
			data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox"
			data-wp-style--right="state.imageButtonRight"
			data-wp-style--top="state.imageButtonTop"
		>
			<svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="12" height="12" fill="none" viewBox="0 0 12 12">
				<path fill="#fff" d="M2 0a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v2h1.5V2a.5.5 0 0 1 .5-.5h2V0H2Zm2 10.5H2a.5.5 0 0 1-.5-.5V8H0v2a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h2v-1.5ZM8 12v-1.5h2a.5.5 0 0 0 .5-.5V8H12v2a2 2 0 0 1-2 2H8Zm2-12a2 2 0 0 1 2 2v2h-1.5V2a.5.5 0 0 0-.5-.5H8V0h2Z" />
			</svg>
		</button></figure>



<div class="alignright wp-block-bloginabox-theme-kicker" data-bi-an="Kicker Left">
	<div class="kicker">
		<h2 class="kicker__title">
			What is threat detection and response?		</h2>
		<p class="kicker__content">
							<a
					href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/business/security-101/what-is-threat-detection-response-tdr"
					class="kicker__link"
					target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"				>
						Read more. 							↗</a>
					</p>
	</div>
</div>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item"><strong>SecOps</strong>: Strengthening threat detection and response capabilities through Microsoft Defender for Identity, Defender for Endpoint, Defender for Office, Defender for Cloud Apps, Defender XDR, and Microsoft Sentinel.</li>
</ul>


<figure data-wp-context="{&quot;imageId&quot;:&quot;6882923cea74e&quot;}" data-wp-interactive="core/image" class="wp-block-image size-full wp-lightbox-container"><img decoding="async" data-wp-class--hide="state.isContentHidden" data-wp-class--show="state.isContentVisible" data-wp-init="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox" data-wp-on-async--load="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async-window--resize="callbacks.setButtonStyles" src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/screenshot.webp" alt="Image of the Security Operations Pillar of the Zero Trust workshop." class="wp-image-141140 webp-format" srcset="" data-orig-src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/screenshot.webp"><button
			class="lightbox-trigger"
			type="button"
			aria-haspopup="dialog"
			aria-label="Enlarge image: Image of the Security Operations Pillar of the Zero Trust workshop."
			data-wp-init="callbacks.initTriggerButton"
			data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox"
			data-wp-style--right="state.imageButtonRight"
			data-wp-style--top="state.imageButtonTop"
		>
			<svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="12" height="12" fill="none" viewBox="0 0 12 12">
				<path fill="#fff" d="M2 0a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v2h1.5V2a.5.5 0 0 1 .5-.5h2V0H2Zm2 10.5H2a.5.5 0 0 1-.5-.5V8H0v2a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h2v-1.5ZM8 12v-1.5h2a.5.5 0 0 0 .5-.5V8H12v2a2 2 0 0 1-2 2H8Zm2-12a2 2 0 0 1 2 2v2h-1.5V2a.5.5 0 0 0-.5-.5H8V0h2Z" />
			</svg>
		</button></figure>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">These additions highlight the Microsoft commitment to a holistic approach to security: helping to better enable organizations with strategies and tools not only to strengthen protection against cyberthreats but also to detect and respond to incidents effectively. The full workshop has been tested by early adopting customers and partners, and the feedback has been very exciting:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote has-quote-default-font-size is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p class="has-body-large-font-size wp-block-paragraph"><em>“You’ve captured the Zero Trust model better than any other [Cloud Solution Provider</em>] <em>CSP in the market. It’s very well-articulated and aligns very strongly with the way we approach it.” </em></p>



<p class="has-body-large-font-size wp-block-paragraph"><em>—Denis O&#8217;Shea, Founder and Chief Executive Officer, Mobile Mentor</em></p>
</blockquote>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading has-h-2-font-size" id="richer-guidance-connecting-the-dots">Richer guidance connecting the dots</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">In addition to adding the three new pillars, we’ve made significant enhancements to the workshop based on your feedback: </p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item"><strong>Implementation effort and user impact indicators</strong>: Now every step in any given pillar of the workshop comes with a high-level estimate of how much effort it would require of your team to deploy, as well as how much of an impact it would have on your users—to help you fully assess when your team and your organization can take on each step.</li>
</ul>


<figure data-wp-context="{&quot;imageId&quot;:&quot;6882923ceda6b&quot;}" data-wp-interactive="core/image" class="wp-block-image size-full wp-lightbox-container"><img decoding="async" data-wp-class--hide="state.isContentHidden" data-wp-class--show="state.isContentVisible" data-wp-init="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox" data-wp-on-async--load="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-async-window--resize="callbacks.setButtonStyles" src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture5.webp" alt="Image focusing on the implementation of effort of the Zero Trust Workshop." class="wp-image-140939 webp-format" srcset="" data-orig-src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture5.webp"><button
			class="lightbox-trigger"
			type="button"
			aria-haspopup="dialog"
			aria-label="Enlarge image: Image focusing on the implementation of effort of the Zero Trust Workshop."
			data-wp-init="callbacks.initTriggerButton"
			data-wp-on-async--click="actions.showLightbox"
			data-wp-style--right="state.imageButtonRight"
			data-wp-style--top="state.imageButtonTop"
		>
			<svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="12" height="12" fill="none" viewBox="0 0 12 12">
				<path fill="#fff" d="M2 0a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v2h1.5V2a.5.5 0 0 1 .5-.5h2V0H2Zm2 10.5H2a.5.5 0 0 1-.5-.5V8H0v2a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h2v-1.5ZM8 12v-1.5h2a.5.5 0 0 0 .5-.5V8H12v2a2 2 0 0 1-2 2H8Zm2-12a2 2 0 0 1 2 2v2h-1.5V2a.5.5 0 0 0-.5-.5H8V0h2Z" />
			</svg>
		</button></figure>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item"><strong>Connecting the cross-pillars scenarios</strong>: In our Zero Trust deployment conversations with customers, one of the biggest challenges they’ve raised is implementing scenarios that span multiple Zero Trust pillars. These scenarios are difficult because they typically involve different teams and stakeholders across their organization. The updated workshop now explicitly highlights these cross-pillar scenarios and identifies the relevant owners, helping customers bring the right people into the discussion and align on next steps.</li>
</ul>


<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture6.webp" alt="Image of specific steps of the Zero Trust workshop." class="wp-image-140940 webp-format" srcset="" data-orig-src="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/Picture6.webp"></figure>



<div class="wp-block-buttons is-content-justification-center is-layout-flex wp-container-core-buttons-is-layout-13 wp-block-buttons-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-button has-custom-width wp-block-button__width-75"><a class="wp-block-button__link wp-element-button" href="https://aka.ms/ZTWorkshop">Try the new and expanded Zero Trust workshop</a></div>
</div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="we-re-committed-to-helping-you-secure-your-organization">We’re committed to helping you secure your organization</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">The Microsoft Zero Trust workshop is more than a training session—it’s a call to action for organizations to reimagine their approach to security in the modern digital landscape and operationalize this vision. With the expanded pillars, this workshop now includes comprehensive insights for implementing a Zero Trust strategy that covers posture, prevention, detection, and response. <a href="https://aka.ms/ZTWorkshop">Give it a try today</a>.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">We are committed to enabling our partners to utilize the workshop to assist our mutual customers in implementing comprehensive security solutions. If you are one of our valued partners, please review our <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/security/zero-trust/zero-trust-partner-kit">Zero Trust partner kit</a>.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Use the Zero Trust workshop together with the <a href="https://aka.ms/ztdocs">Zero Trust guidance center</a> and learn more about the <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/business/zero-trust">Zero Trust security framework</a>. </p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">If you have feedback to share with us about the workshop, please provide it <a href="https://aka.ms/ztworkshop/feedback">here</a>.</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">To learn more about Microsoft Security solutions, visit our <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/business">website.</a> Bookmark the <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/security/blog/">Security blog</a> to keep up with our expert coverage on security matters. Also, follow us on LinkedIn (<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/showcase/microsoft-security/">Microsoft Security</a>) and X (<a href="https://twitter.com/@MSFTSecurity">@MSFTSecurity</a>) for the latest news and updates on cybersecurity.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
https://aka.ms/ztworkshop/feedback
</div></figure>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/2025/07/09/microsoft-expands-zero-trust-workshop-to-cover-network-secops-and-more/">Microsoft expands Zero Trust workshop to cover network, SecOps, and more</a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog">Microsoft Security Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Enhancing Microsoft 365 security by eliminating high-privilege access </title>
		<link>https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/2025/07/08/enhancing-microsoft-365-security-by-eliminating-high-privilege-access/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Naresh Kannan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 19:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/?p=140906</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>​In this blog you will hear directly from Microsoft’s Deputy Chief Information Security Officer (CISO) for Experiences and Devices, Naresh Kannan, about eliminating high-privileged access across all Microsoft 365 applications. This blog is part of an ongoing series where our Deputy CISOs share their thoughts on what is most important in their respective domains. In this series you will get practical advice and forward-looking commentary on where the industry is going, as well as tactics you should start (and stop) deploying, and more. </p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/2025/07/08/enhancing-microsoft-365-security-by-eliminating-high-privilege-access/">Enhancing Microsoft 365 security by eliminating high-privilege access </a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog">Microsoft Security Blog</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<hr class="wp-block-separator has-alpha-channel-opacity"/>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><em>In this blog you will hear directly from Microsoft’s Deputy Chief Information Security Officer (CISO) for Experiences and Devices, Naresh Kannan, about eliminating high-privileged access across all Microsoft 365 applications. This blog is part of an ongoing series where our Deputy CISOs share their thoughts on what is most important in their respective domains. In this series you will get practical advice and forward-looking commentary on where the industry is going, as well as tactics you should start (and stop) deploying, and more.</em>&nbsp;</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Microsoft’s <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/microsoft-cloud/resources/built-in-security" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Secure Future Initiative</a> (SFI) brings together every part of Microsoft to strengthen cybersecurity protection across our infrastructure, products and services. As part of the Protect Tenants and Isolate Production Systems pillar, one of the key objectives is to ensure continuous <strong>least privilege enforcement</strong> by eliminating high-privileged access across all Microsoft 365 applications.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<div class="wp-block-buttons is-content-justification-center is-layout-flex wp-container-core-buttons-is-layout-14 wp-block-buttons-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-button"><a class="wp-block-button__link wp-element-button" href="https://www.microsoft.com/trust-center/security/secure-future-initiative" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Learn more about the Secure Future Initiative</a></div>
</div>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">High-privileged access (HPA) occurs when an application or service obtains broad access to customer content, allowing it to impersonate other users without providing any proof of user context. For example, Applications A and B may have a service-to-service (S2S) relationship to deliver a specific customer scenario. Application A owns and manages customer content in its storage. If Application B can access customer content stored in Application A by calling APIs without a user context, then this is categorized as HPA. </p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">HPA allows for the assumption of any user&#8217;s identity within the service, which can substantially increase the security risk in the event of a service compromise, credential mishandling, or token exposure. &nbsp;</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Given that <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/microsoft-365/products-apps-services" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Microsoft 365 applications</a> interact with one another to deliver rich value and empower critical customer business scenarios, it is crucial for Microsoft to ensure all first-party application interactions involve least privilege access. This is applicable in both where the applications are acting on behalf of a user and services that are not acting on behalf of a user.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="microsoft-s-approach-to-access-rights">Microsoft&#8217;s approach&nbsp;to access rights</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">Eliminating HPA ensures that users and applications have only the necessary access rights. Our strategy within Microsoft’s internal Microsoft 365 environment involved fostering an ‘assume breach’ mindset, with a focus on the stringent enforcement of new standard authentication protocols. With this approach, we have successfully mitigated more than 1,000 high-privilege application scenarios thus far. Achieving this was a monumental cross-functional effort at Microsoft, engaging more than 200 engineers across the company.&nbsp;</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">First, we reviewed all existing Microsoft 365 applications and their S2S interactions with all resource providers across the stack. Second, we deprecated legacy authentication protocols that supported HPA patterns. Third, we accelerated the enforcement of new secure authentication protocols to ensure that all S2S interactions operate within the least-privileged scope required to meet the scenarios.&nbsp;</p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">In many cases, this also required re-engineering the existing architecture and platform to ensure that customer scenarios are accommodated with secure, least privilege access. We ensured that Microsoft 365 first-party applications are interacting with customer content only with the least privilege access. For instance, if Application C has a requirement to read data from specific SharePoint sites, it is granted granular ‘Sites.Selected’ permission rather than ‘Sites.Read.All’ permission. Finally, we have also implemented standardized monitoring systems to identify and report any high-privilege access within Microsoft 365 applications.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="microsoft-security-posture-recommendations">Microsoft security posture recommendations&nbsp;</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">To enhance your organization&#8217;s security posture, we recommend leveraging the native capabilities of Microsoft 365 and implementing these four best practices for safeguarding environments and ensuring the principle of the least privilege access to applications.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<div class="alignright wp-block-bloginabox-theme-kicker" data-bi-an="Kicker Left">
	<div class="kicker">
		<h2 class="kicker__title">
			What is the Microsoft Indentity Platform?		</h2>
		<p class="kicker__content">
							<a
					href="https://learn.microsoft.com/entra/identity-platform/v2-overview"
					class="kicker__link"
					target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"				>
						Learn more							↗</a>
					</p>
	</div>
</div>



<ol class="wp-block-list">
<li class="wp-block-list-item">Audit the existing applications that have access to your data—revoke any unused permissions and reduce excessive permissions.&nbsp;&nbsp;</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Use the Microsoft Entra identity platform’s consent framework to mandate human consent when applications request access to customer content. Utilize delegated permissions in scenarios where an application acts on behalf of a signed-in user. These permissions allow the application to access resources that the user has access to.&nbsp;&nbsp;</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Develop applications with the principle of least-privilege access in mind, throughout all stages of development.&nbsp;&nbsp;</li>



<li class="wp-block-list-item">Employ strict audit controls to periodically review all applications and ensure they adhere to the principle of least privilege access.&nbsp;&nbsp;</li>
</ol>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="learn-more-with-microsoft-security">Learn more&nbsp;with Microsoft Security</h2>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"><a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/entra/identity-platform/secure-least-privileged-access" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Read this article</a> to understand how to improve security with the principle of least privilege. </p>



<div class="wp-block-buttons is-content-justification-center is-layout-flex wp-container-core-buttons-is-layout-15 wp-block-buttons-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-button"><a class="wp-block-button__link wp-element-button" href="http://aka.ms/SecureFutureInitiative" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Discover more about the Microsoft Secure Future Initiative</a></div>
</div>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph">To learn more about Microsoft Security solutions, visit our <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/business" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">website.</a> Bookmark the <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/security/blog/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Security blog</a> to keep up with our expert coverage on security matters. Also, follow us on LinkedIn (<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/showcase/microsoft-security/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Microsoft Security</a>) and X (<a href="https://twitter.com/@MSFTSecurity" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">@MSFTSecurity</a>) for the latest news and updates on cybersecurity.&nbsp;<a id="_msocom_1"></a></p>



<p class="wp-block-paragraph"></p>
<p>The post <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog/2025/07/08/enhancing-microsoft-365-security-by-eliminating-high-privilege-access/">Enhancing Microsoft 365 security by eliminating high-privilege access </a> appeared first on <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/blog">Microsoft Security Blog</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
